<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Achyut Joshi</title>
    <description>Entrepreneur, Avid Traveller, IITian, Skeptic, Hustler and a lifelong learner. I share my life through this blog.
</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2019 17:40:30 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 May 2019 17:40:30 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.6.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Dictionary Based Models for Analysing Multi-Lingual Texts</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;With the increase in the accessibility of technology, language barriers have slowly started to break down. The world has started to mix these languages in order to make communication more intuitive and easy. This can very evidently be seen in multi lingual countries like India, Turkey, etc. I spent the early months of 2019 trying to understand and learn the processes to analyse such multi-lingual texts. I am planning to write a series of posts explaining my findings and learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the world of complex models, bag-of-words or dictionary based models are still one of the most intuitive language models one can think of. A bag-of-words model, or BoW for short, is a way of extracting features from text for use in modelling, such as with machine learning algorithms. The model is only concerned with whether known words occur in the document, not where in the document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is code mixing?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Code-Mixing or Code-Switching is a phenomenon of mixing grammatical structures of two or more languages under varied social constraints. To simplify, whenever you use more than one language in a sentence, you are code mixing. Computationally, natural language analysis has progressed exponentially in terms of mono-lingual texts. However, the research community is still finding ways to process multi-lingual texts. One of the major bottleneck is - data. When it comes to mono-lingual data, it is widely and easily available. But when it comes to code-mixed data, it is a tad bit harder to find. It becomes even more difficult for languages like Hindi that has a different script (Devnagri script) and it is transliterated into roman script when it is code mixed with English.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why dictionary based models?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dictionary based models provide a simple baseline model for such cases. The motivation behind such a model is that we create dictionaries for words of individual languages. For instance if we were analysing a potential candidate for English-Spanish code mixing, we will have two separate dictionaries of words - one for English and another for Spanish. Further, we would create a token based algorithm that compares every word with these dictionaries and returns a metric that captures the code mixing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly this simple method has been used in various domains within the world of Natural language processing - topic modelling, text classification, spam/hate speech detection, etc. Although with the increase in computational capabilities, the state of the art has slowly moved towards deep learning and neural nets, simple bag of words model prove to be a great way to quickly build a baseline model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the advantages of such an approach are -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Easy and intuitive - You exactly know what is going on inside your algorithm and why the results are accurate or not. On the other hand, neural nets and deep learning models are harder to understand.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Computationally easy - Since there are not many parameters to learn, they are much faster than other complex models.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some drawbacks -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Need of large corpus - Unlike neural nets, such models don’t learn and adapt on their own. The model is as good as the data is.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Close association with rule based models - And hence models are more susceptible to human biases.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The independence assumption - all features about order or structure of words in the document are discarded and only mapping with the dictionary corpus is considered&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dictionary based model in identifying Code mixing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked with a specific use case of identifying code mixing in social media conversation between English and Hindi. I worked with three datasets - r/India Reddit comments from January 2017, Bollywood songs lyrics and tweets from select handles. Due to the work by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aclweb.org/anthology/W18-3206&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Deepthi Mave,etal&lt;/a&gt;, I could use the annotated dataset to test the performance. I also gathered various different corpuses which provided me with English &amp;amp; Hindi (in roman script) words. Using this dataset, I used the idea presented by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lrec-conf.org/proceedings/lrec2016/pdf/669_Paper.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Gamback etal&lt;/a&gt; to calculate CMI index to quantify code-mixing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This specific post is to discuss various challenges faced while working with the specific Hindi and English words corpuses. I would be following this blog post with detailed description of the model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tackling Transliteration and small corpus size.&lt;/strong&gt; In spite of the fact that Hindi has a native script, most of the Hindi social media text is transliterated. Due to lack of standardisation in transliteration, a single Hindi word can have multiple surface forms (e.g. Khushboo, Khushbu, Khushbuu etc.). Moreover, because of this, there are no exhaustive datasets available for transliterated Hindi words.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overlapping words.&lt;/strong&gt;
There are many words which overlaps in both languages. When 1 million most frequently used words from Google n-gram data was cross referenced with the corpus of transliterated Hindi words, there were around 5000 English words that were in the Hindi corpus. Some examples were -  rat (night), hue(happened), man(mind), is (this), etc. Moreover, among these words there were instances of words like rani, rasta, etc that has origins in Hindi however because of its common usage are considered to be english words too.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keeping in mind the motive of identifying code mixing instances, I followed a multi-step process of creating a filtered version of these word dictionaries to tackle the above mentioned challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;image height=&quot;300em&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/nlp1.png&quot;&gt; &lt;/image&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some key assumptions and their reasons -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Why removing english words occurring in Mieliestronk’s list? The list contains 58000 English words which have no words having origins from Hindi words. Since the Hindi dictionary was created using social media conversations, it had common english words like road, engineering etc.  Using this list, such words were removed.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the English dictionary that was created using Google n-grams dataset, there were common Hindi-origin words that were considered to be English words (rani (queen), rasta(road), cheetah(tiger)). To get rid of such instances, all words having less frequency(number of occurrences in Google n-gram dataset) than the 50 percentile and also occurring in the Hindi dictionary were removed. The 50 percentile cutoff was chosen because other words were either proper nouns (like yahoo, usa, elizabeth etc) or single letter words (like a, i, etc).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Further improvements&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get more data - I am currently working on developing a model that transliterates devnagri script into roman literals for Hindi.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Further we can use phonetic similarity to tackle non-standard spellings in transliterated Hindi words.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also developing an open source tool &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/achyutjoshi/LangRazor&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;LangRazor&lt;/a&gt; which eases the process of calculating such indexes. Currently it only works for bi-lingual data, but I am hoping to extend it to analyse code-mixing between more than two languages.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2019 15:13:39 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/datascience/dictionary-based-models-code-mixing-nlp</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/datascience/dictionary-based-models-code-mixing-nlp</guid>
        
        
        <category>datascience</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why we Sleep by Mathew Walker</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I have always been fascinated by sleep. I have had my parents advice me to sleep well before every exam - but obviously I never did. I took up this book to understand why people usually stress a lot on good sleep. And 15 pages into this book, I kept this book aside and slept because it was already thirty minutes past my bed time. And ironically even the author suggests the reader to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Should you feel drowsy and fall asleep while reading the book, unlike most authors, I will not be disheartened. Indeed, based on the topic and content of this book, I am actively going to encourage that kind of behaviour from you&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Detailed Highlights and Notes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using Kindle has made sharing highlights and notes pretty easy. I have my personal highlights, however when I was deciding whether I should read this book, I came across this detailed notes from this book which would serve its purpose well - &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.askeladdencapital.com/dr-matthew-walkers-why-we-sleep-book-review-notes-analysis/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Poor Ash’s Almanack&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Things I knew about sleep before I read this book&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We all have heard this - “Sleep is very important”. It helps our brain and body get the much deserved rest.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sleep also helps in recovering emotionally.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are two different stages of sleep - REM and NREM. Although I never exactly understood the difference.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dreams are very often related to our daily emotional state - if we are depressed, our dreams will reflect that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Which opinions were created/changed after reading the book?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is a very complex scientific process that the body undergoes to keep in track sleep and the biological cycle at large. There are two major hormones that help the body - melatonin (helps regulate biological timing) and adenosine (acts like sleep pressure).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Caffeine masks the very effect adenosine and hence tricks the body to be active, in spite of it needing the sleep. One very alarming fact about caffeine is the very long half-life. A 2PM cup of coffee will still has a certain residual affect at 11PM at night.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I have personally woken up exactly two minutes before my alarm whenever I had a big day. It was fascinating to know that this happens to everyone.While our conscious mapping of time is lost during sleep, at a non-conscious level, time continues to be cataloged by the brain with incredible precision.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Time is usually elongated in dreams. Whenever I fall asleep between two alarms, it feels like I lived a whole day within a dream in spite of having a mere 10 minute difference between the alarms.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Night owls and early risers are not who they are by choice. It is not their conscious decision, rather their genetic fate. Interestingly if you think about it, the cultural norm are very biased towards early risers. Even personally, I have tried to create a habit of waking up early quite many times.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is usually very hard to acclimate to a new time zone when travelling eastward than when flying westward. The major reason - eastward direction requires that you fall asleep earlier than you would normally, which is a tall biological order for the mind to simply will into action. While the westward direction requires you to stay up later, which is consciously and practically an easier option. Now I know why it is tough to beat jet-lag when travelling back home to India from the US!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;REM or Rapid Eye Movement Sleep is when the brain is as active as when we are awake. REM is where we dream. The brain paralyses our body during REM cycle so that the brain can dream safely.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;NREM is where the brain eases off into a slow-wave sleep which triggers a state of inward reflection—one that fosters information transfer and the distillation of memories. Think of this as slow AM waves - they have a longer range. These long-range brainwaves of NREM will move memory packets (recent experiences) from a short-term storage site, which is fragile, to a more permanent, and thus safer, long-term storage location.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Humans will have a very different circadian cycle at different ages in their life. Inside a mother’s womb, the sleep in majorly dominated by REM since it establishes a neuro architecture - a framework that will engender thoughts, memories, feelings, decisions and actions. Toddlers ought to have a polyphasic sleep because the part of the brain that controls the circadian cycle takes time to develop. For adolescent teenagers, the cycle moves a bit forward and hence most teenagers want to stay up till late. These biological facts are something we as humans should know - somethings are just beyond our control!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An average human has a stable balance of 80/20 NREM-to-REM ratio. Things are very different for infants wherein the ratio is almost 50/50. The author beautifully expresses this as an act of modelling and remodelling. REM in infants act like a creator - someone who establishes neural highways. While NREM in later part(particularly childhood) helps in maintaining and remodelling according to experiences. If we think about it, this is the reason why childhood plays such an important role in moulding a human brain.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I never knew that sleep and memory are intensively linked. Sleep before learning moves old stuff out to an external hard drive, creating room for the new; sleep after learning makes sure that stuff gets stored instead of lost. There are scientific methods like - sleep stimulation by audio waves to improve NREM sleep and targeted memory reactivation that researchers are experimenting with.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;While NREM is majorly associated with learning, REM is the phase that helps in emotional stability through dreaming. REM-sleep dreaming offers a form of overnight therapy. That is, REM-sleep dreaming takes the painful sting out of difficult, even traumatic, emotional episodes you have experienced during the day, offering emotional resolution when you awake the next morning.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;REM dreaming also fosters problem solving and creativity. In this phase, the brain is no longer constrained to see the most obvious connections. It becomes very actively biased towards seeking out the most distant, non-obvious links between two sets of information. Maybe this is why most of our dreams constitutes random un-related experiences from our brain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How can I use the lessons learnt from this book in my real life?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Since caffeine remains in the body for at least 5-6 hours, I decided not to consume coffee after 4PM.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sleep deprived driving is more dangerous than drunk driving. And this fact has made me more careful whenever I or someone I know travels at night!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And to sum the whole book - I have grown more conscious about how important sleep is. And I would start investing in making my sleep better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Any links with previous books I have read?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is fascinating to learn about how life evolved on Earth. Homo Sapiens have walked through a great journey of evolution to reach the current version of us. The author hinted of how sleep could have been our primary phase of life and slowly we evolved into being awake more.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Yuval Harari in Sapiens explained how the brain size got bigger once we started walking on two legs and how the fact that we can create myths evolved us into the most dominant species on Earth. This books seconds that idea and relates how REM sleep helped in making emotional and cognitive connection between thoughts. This book will definitely rank up top with Sapiens in terms of knowledge I gained!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2019 10:13:39 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/books/why-we-sleep</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/books/why-we-sleep</guid>
        
        
        <category>books</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Thailand #2 : The non-travel bucket-list for your solo - Questions, thoughts and more </title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One week leading to the Thailand trip, I set out to write a long list of fears I wanted to conquer through the whole experience. I even asked several of my close friends to help me point those out.   Many times while travelling we tend to forget that along with the luxury of relaxation, we have an opportunity to really step out of our comfort zone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many of us can really say that between the busy schedule of managing our work, home &amp;amp; relationships we find time to improve our own self? Those who do, please please please, shoot me an email on how you manage it. And for other mortal beings(like me) who don’t, next time you travel, make sure you follow some of these -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have conversations with yourself&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might sound creepy and psychic, but it is fun. And you don’t have to talk aloud or write. Choose your way of implementation. But there is a difference between thinking and “talking” with yourself. Thoughts tend to be more unidirectional when our mind has already decided on a thing. But when you talk, you actually discuss and then decide. I know it sounds creepy, but try it once. I personally wrote those conversations in my diary.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;List down your fears and try to overcome them&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our hectic schedule we never find enough time to work on your flaws and overcome your fears. One of the best things I did before starting the solo was to list down a couple of things I really want to transform. One was the fear of talking to strangers. The first couple of days were tough, but then because I was alone, I HAD to talk to people. I followed a five-second rule - wherein, if I saw a fellow traveller with whom I wanted to talk, I never thought about it for more than five seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make time for a passion of yours&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember that you always wanted to learn a guitar but never could find the time? Or you wanted to binge read a novel, but every time you set out to read one at night, you doze off to sleep? You can guess where I am getting at. You will have all the time in the world to find that quality time. Go and indulge in that passion of yours!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bring back something that reminds you of the trip&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before my trip to Thailand, I was vehemently against spending money on souvenirs. However, while I was bust travelling there, I had this immense urge of taking back a physical something that will remind me of the trip. It can be anything from a conventional souvenir to tattoos or even just a small seashell. I brought back a leather bracelet from the much famous Chiang Mai night market, and I always have in on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Write&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know I preach about this a lot. But, it has been my best companion, so why not? I would recommend writing daily, however, I know it can get a bit cumbersome. Then at least write twice on the whole trip - one when you start the trip and one when you end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Take a cooking course&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might not be applicable to all destinations, but if you are visiting an exotic country which has a rich cuisine, just take the course. I would suggest to take it in the first few days itself because it will provide you with the knowledge of all the dishes the country has to offer. And that makes your life easier when you are ordering food at that small road-side food stall.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 08:13:39 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/travel/bucket-list-for-solo-trip</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/travel/bucket-list-for-solo-trip</guid>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Thailand #1 : In conversation with a Buddhist Monk who is now my Facebook friend </title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I have been really fascinated by Buddhism - especially the intense devotion and motivation of the people to study the religion. To be frank, I was never curious about learning about Hinduism and I don’t see many being curious about the same. I met several people in Thailand who have been staying there for months to learn more about the teaching of the Buddha and practice meditation. There sure must be something of Buddhism which even attracts several atheists to give religion a shot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there I was, walking into Wat Chedi Luang - a buddhist temple in Chiang Mai, on scorching Saturday afternoon with the hope of attending the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bigboytravel.com/asia/thailand/chiangmai/monk-chat/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;“Monk Chat”&lt;/a&gt;. The northern part of the temple has some tables where the monks welcome curious travellers to interact with them who in turn get the chance to practice their English. What I imagined to be a good short &amp;amp; an awkward conversation, turned into a two-hour intense discussion about life, goals, meditation and death. An American couple from Texas joined us on the table, and if I may say, we all left a bit wiser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;image class=&quot;center-img&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/thailand1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/image&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I so wish I could have recorded the discussion, but then maybe it was better that it took place in the moment. I have tried to accumulate all that we discussed on that day, and as you will observe, the monk always had a simple anecdote to explain a complex idea :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is so different about Buddhism that it attracts so many people?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has always been this curiosity regarding what is different in various religions that the human race follows. I used to believe that religion is something that divides the human race and have been the fire to some of the world’s deadliest wars. However, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.in/gp/product/0099590085/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=3638&amp;amp;creative=24630&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0099590085&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=achyutjoshi-21&amp;amp;linkId=da749671e8b9d0ed6acb52ee0a1ded7a&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;Sapiens&lt;/a&gt; made me realise that the concept has equipped us to bring humans closer.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I asked this to the monk, he had a pretty interesting take on it. He drew a river of which, on one side is where all humans exist, and the other he termed as the “Happy Land”, where everyone wants to go. He then showcased three teachers, who are followers of three distinct religions. For Buddhism, he shared that Buddha &amp;amp; his teachings can only guide you how to build a boat, but the real work of building it and crossing the river is on the human. Every religion will have a different way to build that boat - but, in every case, the end goal is the same.   Buddhism does not force its followers to visit temples and perform certain rituals - but they sure do exist if you want to be a monk. But as a normal person, you are free to follow the teachings and consider yourself as a Buddhist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do the teachings of Buddha suggest the followers to give up materialistic possessions and live an aesthetic life?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nope. Never. As a matter of fact, the monk showed me his Apple tablet with a wide grin. He went on to narrate the story of Gautam Buddha and how he attained salvation. Buddha preaches that the life you are living is yours, and you are independent of living it the way you want. Earn money, buy a big house, but do good. Be good, do good and spread happiness, and it does not matter if you are the richest or the poorest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What controls our life? Does past affect us?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always wondered how the cycle of life works. How our past sins can carry forward in our next birth and are we really stuck in a cycle of death-rebirth-death?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  The monk took out his water bottle and told us to imagine the water as our life. Whenever we do evil, we add blue ink to it. And whenever we do good, we add clean water to it. The goal of the life is to try and maintain the water to be as clean as possible. Buddhism, as he suggested, does not take past sins into considerations - you always live in the now. Even a murderer can achieve moksha if he does good in the remaining life time he has.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What happens after we die? Hell, heaven, nirvana?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disclaimer : this particular answer was lost in translation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; 
But as far as I can remember, heaven &amp;amp; hell is down on earth itself. If you are a drunk husband misbehaving at your home, it is hell for you. But if you are a loving man, you make it heaven for your family. The everyday activities determine whether we are living in hell or heaven. And about nirvana, that is what every person aspires to reach. He tried explaining what nirvana is, but I could not make sense out of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Buddhism talks a lot about doing good. How to do good?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude. Respect. Forgiveness. One can never articulate on how to do good - it is a matter of perspective. However, if you follow such practices in your daily life, you will eventually spread happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  The monk narrated how they are given jobs in the temples, right from sweeping the floor, washing clothes to cooking food. It teaches them to be grateful of what they have. And pointing to his trademark smile, he said, this is the one of the most powerful weapon we have. Smile as much as you can, and you will see the difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is meditation?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything is meditation. If you are giving your 100% to a certain activity, it is meditation. Religions and teachers preach the very specific meditation that we learn because it is easier to close your eyes and focus on your breathing. But the end goal of this activity is to train ourselves to live in the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  &lt;em&gt;I would suggest you to stop reading and contemplate what the monk meant by this!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is one thing you would want us to do more in life?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are my favourite types of question because it forces the person to think.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The monk went on to express how the digital age has forced our mind to wander off and not concentrate on one thing. “There are too many distractions”, he said while showing off his mobile phone. He said he would really want us to practice meditation, everyday. He also suggested to learn and live in the present. As a generation who is known to be competitive, we sure do tend to miss out on the little things in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do monks eat meat?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monks are dependent on alms and donations given by the people around the town( I was lucky to witness this solemn practice where monks walked around the city centre of Chiang Mai in the morning to collect alms). Therefore, as monks they do not have much choice and have to accept what they receive. However, the scripture sure do restrict eating certain animals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who is Dalai Lama and why are there no picture of him in Thailand?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two groups in Buddhism - Mahayana &amp;amp; Thervada. Theravada Buddhism is prevalent in countries like Sri Lanka, Thailand, Burma, Laos, Cambodia, parts of Southeast Asia. On the other hand, Mahayana Buddhism is prevalent in countries like Tibet, China, Taiwan, Japan, Korea, Mongolia, India. Though both the groups are based on the same set of teachings by Buddha, there are certain difference in the way they practice. And Dalai Lama is the spiritual head of the Mahayana sect of the religion and therefore Thailand is totally void of any presence of him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know for a fact that I am missing out on a lot of things that we talked, but I don’t seem to remember them. I tried to paraphrase most of the wisdom as much as I could remember from my notes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 Mar 2018 07:13:39 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/travel/learnings-from-buddhist-monks-in-thailand</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/travel/learnings-from-buddhist-monks-in-thailand</guid>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>#6 - Rather than the breadth, lets do the depth!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It has been one week since I returned from my Thailand expedition - and it has not been that bad. Obviously, I don’t think I will ever be satisfied with myself, and that is perfectly okay. So, I hit the gym regularly for the whole week. I set up a good working space at my home - though could not work as much as I wanted to. But at least, there is some start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have always tried to be an all-rounder - doing a good bunch of things whenever I got the chance. It might be because of the way I was brought up or because I have an acute fear of missing out. This has placed me in a box where I am a master of none. Therefore one thing that I have decided is to try going deep into a subject this time. And I spent the later part of the week deciding the field I want to go deep into - a classic case of me fearing of missing out, again! I have already taken up a few things - more on this next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also trying to automate the email updates for my blog through Mailchimp. Though, I need to figure out a way through which MailChimp selects RSS feeds of only certain categories of posts and convert it into a newsletter. And this has to be compatible with Jekyll and Github Pages. I will dig into this more the coming week!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interesting Stumbles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/mimir-blockchain/the-birds-the-bees-and-the-merkle-trees-ep-0-blockchains-from-scratch-3cedb1e669eb&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Blockchain&lt;/a&gt; - I have not completed this, but so far, this post have really helped to know the subject&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCJkMlOu7faDgqh4PfzbpLdg&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Nerdwriter&lt;/a&gt; - An insightful youtube channel that is just a great way to spend time on the internet rather than surfing through the shit called Facebook&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is Us - The newest drama in my list which I binged watched through the week. For all those who are fans of good-old classic drama, This is Us won’t disappoint.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Books,Books and Books&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.in/gp/product/0434023469/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=3638&amp;amp;creative=24630&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0434023469&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=achyutjoshi-21&amp;amp;linkId=63448d3e15ac4d5b82637cd3194e0a02&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Smarter, Faster and Better&lt;/a&gt; -I took up this book after hearing Duhigg talk about Mental Models in a Freakonomics podcast. I have completed around 30% of it it, and so far, there has been nothing extra-ordinary in the book. I have always been a big fan of Duhigg’s writing style, so hopefully this won’t disappoint.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.in/gp/product/0099578077/ref=as_li_qf_asin_il_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=achyutjoshi-21&amp;amp;creative=24630&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0099578077&amp;amp;linkId=c7e966ae5f27509bfa376cf8eba3f0fb&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1Q84&lt;/a&gt; - Murakami has this power of gripping your attention throughout the book. Another masterpiece by this Japanese superstar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Music Discovery&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have often heard my friends telling how they hate finding new music. And yes, it is a pain-staking process. But I have these few hours once every two weeks where I devote the time to discover new music. Why not share them with the world?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=J1yvQznOHNU&amp;amp;list=PLkCUhga4t_lBGSlF94CtJbYK3XWzjog2D&amp;amp;index=5&amp;amp;t=0s&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Parvazz -Khufiya Dastaan&lt;/a&gt; - One of the older gems by this great band&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9cbQoAWL2-8&amp;amp;list=PLkCUhga4t_lBGSlF94CtJbYK3XWzjog2D&amp;amp;index=6&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Vipin Misra Project&lt;/a&gt; - A silk-route member who now has his own band - Another one of the hidden gems of the Indian Indie scene&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-BKHCIVzV38&amp;amp;list=PLkCUhga4t_lBGSlF94CtJbYK3XWzjog2D&amp;amp;index=7&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dream Theatre&lt;/a&gt; - My new work music&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 24 Feb 2018 20:13:39 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/journal/journal-six</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/journal/journal-six</guid>
        
        
        <category>journal</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Pre-trip Musings : Thailand #0</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Just about 12 hours to go before I fly off to my first longish solo travel to the much famous land of smiles. My mind is wandering in all sorts of directions, but the majority opinion of my brain cells is - “What the hell? Don’t go Achyut!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestly, even though this is something that I have dreamt of since I read “Vagabonding” by Rolf Pott, I am shit scared. And my mind is playing the bad cop and giving me reasons not to go. But, nada! Not today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first, I thought I was the only one who is going through something like this. Having cold feet about such a big trip, anxious, nervous and scared. But I went on Reddit and read posts of novice and experienced travellers &amp;amp; they all faced the same issue. I guess this is how our human brain functions - not wanting to leave the comfort zone! And when we try to ignore the arguments, our mind builds a much stronger defence against the change - and that is where most of us give up, and let the mind win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what are my fears right now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Being an over-excited bastard that I am, I booked a 16-day trip without thinking of what I will do. Thank my parents who made me reduce it from 25 days. And now, I am worried of the fact that what will I do if I get bored.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of the biggest fear - what if I don’t meet people and I get lonely throughout the trip? I am not that good a conversation starter, and being the introvert I am - I don’t know if I will be able to meet people. Though all my accommodations are in hostels, let’s see where and how I land up there.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Spending too much  - As you start to book things, you discover new expenditures that totally disrupts your original budget. And this makes you feel guilty and you start to save money by not doing things that you really want to. Sad place to be in, but I am sure this is a very common thing among travellers.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Getting into trouble - missing flights, losing money, etc etc - You can only pre-empt to a certain limit. But I am surely scared of such things - especially because I am alone. Moreover, money is tricky business. A long post on how I managed my money is on the cards, if I return without any mishap :p&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Food - This has never been a big question for me because “I eat to live”. Though, let’s see if I get enough vegetarian food there!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will try to post my experiences every two days. Wish me luck!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2018 07:13:39 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/travel/pre-trip-musings-thailand</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/travel/pre-trip-musings-thailand</guid>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>#5 - Breathing Again.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It has been just 19 days in 2018 and I have realised how different, surprising and unplanned this year is going to be. I left my first job to explore new things and it has been 19 days since and I have not improved my skillset even by a tiny notch. I say I took a break to get to know me more, but in reality I have not done any experiments to say that. Freelancing is not working, or rather I have not put in enough efforts to make it work. I am hardly reading any books. I started gym for a week and then have not worked out since the last five days. I got into a bit of a mix in the personal space.On the whole, I am just letting life slip by during one of the most amazing period of my life, a period which most only dreams of. But, I am just wasting it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deciding what to do?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since I have left college, one thing I have learnt is the life outside the education bubble is very different because you yourself have to set goals, quantify it and then work to achieve it. Schools and colleges have exams, and marks or grades are the usual quantifiers. So it becomes easy. Out here, you are your own teacher and the student too. You have to set yourself a question paper, based on the syllabus you deem fit for you, then appear for it yourself, and finally evaluate too. Isn’t that scary? Yes it is, and it is the reason why most of us try to set a question paper that people have already appeared for. Doing something out-of-box, is scary, because you set out on uncharted waters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took this break from my stint with SocialCops because of this very reason. I wanted to see whether I am made for this exploration of new paths, or should I quietly follow the normal trend. And to be honest, up till now I have failed myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Whats stopping me?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One, home&lt;/strong&gt;
Finally being at home with the intension of staying here, at least for the next three-four months have been comforting and serene. Spending time with my parents and family is very special. However, I am yet to settle down, find a schedule because for the past five years home has always been a holiday for me. And this comfort has brought an inertia which I need to let go off, and that too very fast. It again has to be a place where I learn and grow.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Two, my headspace.&lt;/strong&gt;
I am a bit too emotional and things that don’t go according to me affect me a lot. It affects everything around me and that is something I need to learn - keeping my personal &amp;amp; professional life separate. This will take time, I am sure. But hopefully, as the great Murakami puts it - “ When you come out of this storm, you won’t be the same person who walked in. That’s what this storm is about”. I don’t want to be the same person again!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Three, growth is not always about mastering something for your career.&lt;/strong&gt;
I had planned earlier that I would do certain things so that I can learn a bit more of R, and Python. However, slowly I am realising that maybe I should also focus on things which I would never again get time for. Abstract things, like learning to box or cooking, which will never help me make my career in data, but still it would be fun to learn right?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Four, setting out goals and quantifying it.&lt;/strong&gt;
I have always been bad at this. But when you set out on your own, this becomes very crucial because goals will become your sacrosanct compass that will guide you the way in the dark.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Five, Writing!&lt;/strong&gt;
I have always maintained this position where I say - I write because it forces me to try new things. Well, Achyut, then you need writing more than ever now. So weekly journals will be back. And I am heading to Thailand for a solo in Feb, so expect more of the travel blogs too.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Six,Execute!&lt;/strong&gt;
One of my juniors in college told me - “Achyut, you preach a lot, but you fail in executing things”. And I accept it. And this is the most important of all - execute what you decide.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So what next?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting my ass back to work, starting to step out of my comfort zone again and enjoying!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS. I am actively looking for any freelancing projects in the fields of - Data Science, Designing, Writing, or any shit (I have enough free time and thus will learn something new). So everyone who is reading this, help me get them :D&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2018 20:13:39 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/journal/breathing-again</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/journal/breathing-again</guid>
        
        
        <category>journal</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>#4 - The New Start.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;So, as always, I did not end up making this a habit. Various incidences in my life have forced me to conclude that I can never create a routine of my own. But I badly want to challenge that conclusion and therefore instead of waiting for this to become a habit and then make it public, I will be posting every journal entry on Sundays over my facebook &amp;amp; instagram handle. Game on, life!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to setup goals?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I started my first job, planning and managing my time is something that I am consciously trying to do. And one of the biggest learning that I have had is - “Have quantifiable success/failure measure against each of your goals”. So when you decide to complete a task A, have a measure in mind regarding when will you say that task is completed. It may seem very trivial, however when it comes to implementation, I am yet to discover the most efficient way to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Indonesia VS Philippines/Thailand?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am planning to do a month long backpacking trip to SE-Asia early next year. My main motivation to try this, it to understand whether I really like the concept of long-term travelling or I am a kind of person who just like the concept and does not want to get his hands dirty. I do hope I am not the later. Indonesia has always been on the top of my list, mainly because of a decent backpacking culture and the varied opportunities of learning to dive. However, Jan/Feb being the wettest months in Indonesia, slowly I am skeptical about my plans and I just might head to Philippines or Thailand. If anyone reading has any suggestions for this, please please do let me know :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Science of Productivity?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was listing to this podcast by &lt;a href=&quot;https://lifehacker.com/charles-duhigg-on-self-motivation-mental-models-and-g-1793445660&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Upgrade&lt;/a&gt; where Charles Duhigg talks about various ways and psychologies of being productive. One thing that really struck me was the art of telling stories to your mind. Everyday in the metro, Duhigg closes his eyes and recreates the perfect day in his mind. He trains his brain to live that ideal day in the mind first and so, when it actually happens in real life, his brain already knows what to do. Micheal Phelps used a similar method to recreate a perfect winning swim before he went to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it sounds logical too right? Train your brain for all the worst and the best things you can imagine of, and so when it happens in real-life, it is no different for you. I might try this, though I need to read more on how to do it exactly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Phone Hack!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was reading &lt;a href=&quot;https://betterhumans.coach.me/a-phone-setup-that-will-make-you-more-mindful-1c5d8be7e661?source=rss----7038e003d060---4&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;this blog&lt;/a&gt; where it struck me that even I have become addicted to my phone. Who has not right? In spite of having deleted Facebook, I still end up using Instagram quite regularly. So I followed some of the hacks mentioned in the blog to give my iphone a quick change. And within two days, I actually feel the change. Do give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top things that I read or listened to&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hackernoon.com/spotifys-discover-weekly-how-machine-learning-finds-your-new-music-19a41ab76efe&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Spotify’s Discover Weekly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.twitter.com/engineering/en_us/topics/insights/2017/Our-Discovery-of-Cramming.html?utm_campaign=Data%2BElixir&amp;amp;utm_medium=email&amp;amp;utm_source=Data_Elixir_157&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Why Twitter expanded its word-limit?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dansheffler.com/blog/2014-07-21-two-goals-of-note-taking/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Note Taking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://sethgodin.typepad.com/seths_blog/2017/11/the-boss-goes-first.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The boss goes first&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lifehacker.com/charles-duhigg-on-self-motivation-mental-models-and-g-1793445660&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Upgrade - By Life Hacker&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 18 Nov 2017 20:13:39 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/journal/journal-four</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/journal/journal-four</guid>
        
        
        <category>journal</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>#3 - The Crisis Land.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I missed writing the journal last week because of the Diwali celebrations at home. And there I am, writing this at 12 on a Sunday night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I hate dormancy!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lately I have been too dormant of learning new things. I have kind of got used to completing the day-to-day work and then be satisfied with it. And the worst part? I know I don’t want to, but the motivation and the zeal have kind of flown away. I tried out following a technique - the first 2-3 hours in office, don’t complete the monotonous workload, rather spend these hours in learning new things. However, after two days of following it, something always used to end up on my desk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thoughts?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to beat this dormancy? How to get back up and try to be the person you want to be? Is it because of the kind of workplace I am in, or is it because of me? I believe it is more to do with the kind of routine you follow. The day when you stop stepping out of your comfort zone, is the day you become dormant. I have no plans chalked out to beat this right now. All I have right now, is the intent to change. Hopefully when I write this next week, I have a plan in place :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theatre &amp;amp; Jazz&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least on the trying out new things outside the professional world, I am not that dormant. I attended a beautiful play at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oddbird.org&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;OddBird Theatre&lt;/a&gt;. The kind of intimate setting they had, and the whole experience around it was a first time for me. The organisers forced us to sit with strangers during the play. Also, as soon as everyone was settled in, there was silence for 5 minutes, a beautiful way to allow the audience to vent out all the thoughts before they can be totally attentive to the show. The play was &lt;a href=&quot;https://lbb.in/delhi/events/59f04bb8e470e5506c9b2727/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Tadpole Repertory’s Quicksand&lt;/a&gt;, and anyone who is in Delhi, should absolutely experience this once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After an intensive one-hour of theatre, it was Jazz time for me. Delhi’s much famous &lt;a href=&quot;http://thepianoman.in&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Piano Man&lt;/a&gt; was hosting Sharvi Yadav &amp;amp; Bohemia Voice. Such a musical experience was again a first time for me, and to say the least, it was beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cooking&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One more new thing I did this week was try my hand at cooking. And to my surprise, I discovered cooking to be therapeutic. I did not cook anything fancy, just Egg Bhurji, half-fry and boiled eggs. But however small, it was fun and different. I will for sure cook more often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top Blogs that I read&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://levels.io/eighteen/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;What would I do if I were 18 now&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.data.world/the-near-future-of-data-is-linked-75f4c011f9cf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The near future of data is linked&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://betterhumans.coach.me/financial-freedom-the-missing-link-1b383c806044&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Financial Freedom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2017 21:13:39 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/journal/journal-three</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/journal/journal-three</guid>
        
        
        <category>journal</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>#2 - The Week that was.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It really took some convincing to write this thing today. The only question popped up to me was, “Why should I write it when no one reads it?” But then, I write for myself :)
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Big Launch&lt;/strong&gt;
I was working on a project with the Ministry of Rural Development to develop a dashboard for monitoring 41 national schemes. It was finally launched by the Prime Minister on Wednesday in a grand event at Delhi. Apart from the 5 minutes where he launched our dashboard and spoke about the impact it will create, the event was boring &amp;amp; tiring. But yes, in my first job, the first project gets launched by the Prime Minister - it was surreal. You can read more about the project in this &lt;a href=&quot;https://socialcops.com/case-studies/disha-dashboard/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thoughts?&lt;/strong&gt;
I have started to somewhere doubt my motivation to create a habit and follow it. It has been three months I have been in Delhi and yet I usually waste time when I am not in office. Netflix, youtube and the internet have become a regular time wasting machine. Also, the zeal to convert my ambitions into actions have reduced. Is it because of the job? Or is it just me?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One App that I discovered this week&lt;/strong&gt;
I stumbled upon &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/reflectly-journal/id1241229134?mt=8&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Reflectly&lt;/a&gt;, which is a basic journalling application. The best thing I loved about this particular app, is the fact that is not monotonous. Everyday, the app asks you new questions which really makes you think about your day. Do give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top 3 Blogs that I read&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/applied-data-science/new-r-package-the-xgboost-explainer-51dd7d1aa211&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;XGBoost Explainer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/airbnb-engineering/scaling-knowledge-at-airbnb-875d73eff091&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Scaling Knowledge at AirBnb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/personal-growth/when-it-comes-to-innovation-are-you-a-sculptor-or-a-painter-43713f11f97d&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Sculptor vs Painter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2017 21:13:39 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/journal/journal-two</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/journal/journal-two</guid>
        
        
        <category>journal</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
