<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Achyut Joshi</title>
    <description>Entrepreneur, Avid Traveller, IITian, Skeptic, Hustler and a lifelong learner. I share my life through this blog.
</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2017 22:49:44 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2017 22:49:44 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.4.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Is it really worth it?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Has anyone felt that sheer guilt from within?&lt;br /&gt;
something inside you wants to curse you,&lt;br /&gt;
break you, punch you and pull you down the stairs&lt;br /&gt;
into the infinite void till you cannot match your own sight&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have. And I have known this for long.&lt;br /&gt;
 But still I did nothing. &lt;br /&gt;
Or rather, we did nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four long years back, I left home to pursue my dreams.&lt;br /&gt;
I was always taught to dream big and,&lt;br /&gt;
fortunately or unfortunately,          &lt;br /&gt;
I dreamt bigger that my cosy little home city could provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was this unsaid understanding that         &lt;br /&gt;
one day I will leave home,    &lt;br /&gt;
but never really understood that         &lt;br /&gt;
I will never really be at home after that day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Family gatherings started to become a rarity,  &lt;br /&gt;
Home-food a luxury and festival days just holidays.  &lt;br /&gt;
 But more importantly, I was never there  &lt;br /&gt;
I was never there for them, when they needed the most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When they wanted to learn a new app,&lt;br /&gt;
When they were facing issues with their mobiles,&lt;br /&gt;
When they wanted to be in sync with the modern world&lt;br /&gt;
or when they just wanted a kid in the house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They were always there, always.&lt;br /&gt;
They still are, and here I am,&lt;br /&gt;
trying to open my wings and fly away&lt;br /&gt;
when all they want is to fly with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it really worth it? &lt;br /&gt;
The success. The knowledge&lt;br /&gt;
The degrees. The work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it really worth it?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 06:43:39 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/randomblog/is-it-worth-it</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/randomblog/is-it-worth-it</guid>
        
        
        <category>randomblog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let's borrow a Human : The Human Library Delhi</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Living alone in a big city like Delhi gets boring sometimes, especially on the weekend when you have watched almost everything on Netflix that interests you. But for a bibliophile like me, the city has a lot to offer. Storytelling meetups and workshops to some unique(at least for me!) ideas of borrowing a human for half an hour and reading him/her. Luckily I stumbled upon one such event in Delhi and I couldn’t just miss it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conversations are at the core of this concept. Instead of books, there are real people with real stories, engaging their readers and answering their questions. A reader can choose from a variety of books and have a real conversation with them. Today’s event was a collaboration between Human Library Chapters in four cities - Delhi, Mumbai, Pune &amp;amp; Hyderabad. So instead of having the books sitting across our tables, we were connected over Google Hangouts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole experience was surreal. We had two books(people) from Mumbai who shared their stories with us. One was a 30-32-year-old person, who narrated his experiences of being a Mercedes salesperson to backpacking the South-East Asia circuit and finally after several failed business plans starting a hippie cafe in Mumbai. And the second book was about how a guy fought and overcame the bruises that were caused by being abused in his childhood. They both were contrasting stories - one was funny and entertaining, and the other was gloomy and horrifying. But isn’t that who we really are - people with different sets of experiences and baggages? And listening to the experiences which I could not empathise even in my dreams and discovering the fact that those are so common made me realise how little I know about the world I live in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I fell in love with the whole concept of Human Library today. I am sure I will be attending more of these wherever I go. If you get a chance, do visit one of these, I am certain it will be as heart-warming as it was for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read more about &lt;a href=&quot;http://humanlibrary.org&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Human Library&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/Humanlibrarydelhi/?ref=br_rs&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Delhi Chapter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Aug 2017 06:43:39 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/randomblog/the-human-library-experience</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/randomblog/the-human-library-experience</guid>
        
        
        <category>randomblog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>#1 - Why Journaling?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Yes, I love writing. But lately I have been thinking on the motivation behind it. I have been asked why I write and the best answer I can come up is, it pushes my boundaries, it pushes me to try new things in the first place so I can write about them. And frankly, that is the truth.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have seen many people try weekly journalling and lose their motivation within few weeks. Maybe I would too. But then I cannot not try with this fear right? So here I am, trying my hand at weekly journalling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will list down everything and anything that I want to share in these series of blog posts, which usually on normal weeks will be published on Sunday. The blogs will be raw &amp;amp; unedited so excuse the usage wrong incorrect grammar and sentence structures. I want to make this process as easy as possible so I can create a habit around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Everything going on in this week:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lately I am feeling as if I am letting my life slip by my hand. Work at SocialCops is very hectic and somewhere I lose out on the things I want to do for myself. The life revolves around work-home-work, and which I really hate myself for doing. So, from this week I decided to take a step back, and start getting the control again, be in the drivers seat, and not let life play me around. And it is tough, but if if not done now, I will never learn to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bulletjournal.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Bullet Journaling&lt;/a&gt; is back. The last time I had tried this was in my final year of college when there were less things to manage. But now, when you have multiple projects going on at work, and also several personal projects and things, you need a way for organizing your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Music?&lt;/strong&gt; I stumbled upon the several songs composed by Amit Trivedi for the upcoming movie Secret Superstar. And the songs are Amit Trivedi at his best. Do listen to this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XyZ0aXrpJIc&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From next time I will start sharing great blogs that I read too. I need to figure out a way to best show them though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until next time, see ya!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Aug 2017 06:43:39 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/journal/why-journal</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/journal/why-journal</guid>
        
        
        <category>journal</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Dear Me</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I vividly remember the gloomy evening when&lt;br /&gt;
I boarded Suryanagri Express for the first time. &lt;br /&gt;
Three large suitcases, a bag on the shoulder,&lt;br /&gt;
and a million scattered thoughts.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
My whole family had flooded the Platform 3&lt;br /&gt;
of Vadodara Junction to bid me farewell.&lt;br /&gt;
12480 slowly eases onto the station &lt;br /&gt;
amidst of all the chaos!    &lt;br /&gt;
And why not? It was a routine halt for the train.&lt;br /&gt;
As I rush into my coach, tears start to flood my eyes&lt;br /&gt;
as that one step marked the end of a beautiful chapter of my life.  &lt;br /&gt;
I was leaving for Jodhpur to attend &lt;br /&gt;
my undergraduate course at IIT Jodhpur.  &lt;br /&gt;
For a family that seldom expresses their emotions,&lt;br /&gt;
seeing them cry made me realise the magnitude of the occasion&lt;br /&gt;
I was no more a child.&lt;br /&gt;
I was growing up. We were growing up!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then it happened. It might be cliched, &lt;br /&gt;
but the best days of my life begun.&lt;br /&gt;
Four years is a very long time.&lt;br /&gt;
Jodhpur became a home more than my home&lt;br /&gt;
And the people there became a part of me.&lt;br /&gt;
Seniors who guided me, classmates who walked with me &lt;br /&gt;
and juniors who made my experiences worth sharing.&lt;br /&gt;
Those years made me who I am today, and&lt;br /&gt;
taught me how to live, how to fail,&lt;br /&gt;
how to cry and how to have fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time indeed is a treacherous clown.&lt;br /&gt;
It slows down when we really want to get through tough times &lt;br /&gt;
and it speeds past the memorable days &lt;br /&gt;
leaving behind some amazing memories.&lt;br /&gt;
My undergrad just flew past me, &lt;br /&gt;
without any space to breathe.  &lt;br /&gt;
It so happens, we just live for the time to pass&lt;br /&gt;
without realising the importance.  &lt;br /&gt;
And when the days got numbered,&lt;br /&gt;
I realised all the things I could have done,&lt;br /&gt;
all the conversations I could have made,&lt;br /&gt;
and the moments I could have actually lived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The day came. It started. &lt;br /&gt;
And it was the toughest day of my life.&lt;br /&gt;
10th May it was. The day when we parted,&lt;br /&gt;
the day when I changed.  &lt;br /&gt;
We had stayed up all night because &lt;br /&gt;
4 out of the 16 of us were leaving by a morning train.  &lt;br /&gt;
A planned sober night, which turned into&lt;br /&gt;
a night of a couple of BP shots.  &lt;br /&gt;
And for the final time, and&lt;br /&gt;
maybe the last, we 16 were together in one room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Promises of meeting again, &lt;br /&gt;
tight hugs to show our love,    &lt;br /&gt;
and moist eyes trying hard &lt;br /&gt;
to hold back on those tears.&lt;br /&gt;
And as the clocks neared 5 am, &lt;br /&gt;
we took a final walk of our home,&lt;br /&gt;
laid down on the misty grass of our garden &lt;br /&gt;
and watched the stars in silence&lt;br /&gt;
a silence filled with a million of &lt;br /&gt;
conversations and emotions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Railway stations, airports and bus stops &lt;br /&gt;
are a mecca of goodbyes and farewells.    &lt;br /&gt;
I finally gave up and let the tears flow  &lt;br /&gt;
The final hug, the final glance &lt;br /&gt;
and the green signal&lt;br /&gt;
We were 4 down!&lt;br /&gt;
It should never have been this tough.  &lt;br /&gt;
But then if we had the guts &lt;br /&gt;
to build a friendship this strong,&lt;br /&gt;
Tears ought to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, in the evening my time was up.&lt;br /&gt;
We had somehow gotten used to saying goodbyes.  &lt;br /&gt;
So with simple hugs and a wide smile on my face,&lt;br /&gt;
I boarded the same Suryanagri Express,&lt;br /&gt;
on which I had started this journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So dear me,&lt;br /&gt;
This is how it ended.&lt;br /&gt;
A big part of us died that day,&lt;br /&gt;
a part that will be remembered, cherished&lt;br /&gt;
and missed for the days to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life completes a full circle.&lt;br /&gt;
I cried on the first day,&lt;br /&gt;
because I was scared of what lied ahead.&lt;br /&gt;
And I cried on the last day,&lt;br /&gt;
because I was leaving a part of me behind.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Aug 2017 19:43:39 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/randomblog/dear-me</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/randomblog/dear-me</guid>
        
        
        <category>randomblog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Doing Mcleodganj Solo: Notes by a Novice</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;For people who know me, understand how the word travelling can ignite a spark within me. For me, the only positive of staying in Delhi was being at an overnight distance to most of the destinations in the Himalayas. Three weeks into my first job, I was starting to curse myself for wasting three weekends and so hastily I booked my tickets to Dharamshala and my accommodation at Zostel-Mcleodganj. And this is how I found my north star, something that I can always go back to  - the concept of travelling alone!  
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A normal Friday evening. I left from work at 6. Briskly walked through the Delhi chaos. I reached home and packed a few tees and my bathroom pouch. My kindle and my diary were already sitting inside my bag. I rechecked my tickets, locked my house and started to walk for Saket metro. Usually, I listen to a podcast when I am travelling in the metro, but that Friday evening was different. I just stood near the door, with two small bags and nonchalantly gazed through the people. When I got out, the weather too was experiencing something contrasting - the first proper rains of the season. Finally, after an hour of waiting and navigating through the conundrum called ISBT, I boarded my bus to Dharamshala.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  Mcleodganj is an experience that has been transformed by many travellers, either through their words or pictures. And I am an expert in neither. So, rather than trying to put the trip into words, I will make an attempt to express what Mcleodganj did to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;ना मूज़े हिन्दी आती है,
and neither my English is perfect.     &lt;br /&gt;
But I love writing
और में लिख रहा हू |&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;में वो हू जो अपने आप में रहता है,
But my shells collapse like dominos,             &lt;br /&gt;
जब में लिख रहा होता हू ,
And I am writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was my first, travelling solo. And frankly, I was shit scared. Being someone who finds it difficult to start a conversation and someone who thinks a lot about how others will perceive me, it was supposed to be a nightmare. But in fact, it turned out to be the exact opposite. The two days were a perfect mixture of solitude and meeting some warm &amp;amp; interesting people, which includes a designer from Delhi and an artist from Kolkata who calls himself Pablo. We met in the morning, explored the nooks and crannies of the town, talked about things ranging from college to Buddhism to meditation, had a drink at night and bid farewell to never see each other ever again. Can it get more spontaneous than this?   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The art of doing nothing is something everyone should learn to practice. We always prefer to cut down our commute and take a taxi to the hotel. But imagine walking on the green serene curves of Himalayas, with the early morning drizzles hitting on the road and sometimes making their distinctive sound of dropping in a puddle. It might sound enchanting, but it was a long arduous walk with no map or humanity to guide. I was presented with cross roads every now and then, and sometimes I had to climb back up with my luggage when the road did not feel right. And yet, if given a chance, I would try to make many more mistakes just to walk more. Most people would consider this a big waste of time, but I say, once in a while indulge into doing nothing, just nothing. I sat for a couple of hours at this wooden porch of a cute little hostel in Dharamkot which silently sits hidden behind the majestic Himalayas. A dense cover of fog passes through me as I sip some hot green tea, observing rain drops falling from the ceiling. Apart from that, I was doing nothing. But I was having fun, and that is what matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having travelled the Himalayas a lot, I have visited many Monasteries and there is something different about the religion that has always fascinated me. Is it the calmness of the location or is it the intense devotion of the monks? Or is there a whole new reason yet to be discovered? I am not sure. But I will definitely read more about the religion and its practices which attract millions of people to backpack and spend several months in the little Lhasa. One thing is certain, the Namgyal Monastery, where His Holiness Dalai Lama lives, is a big disappointment, especially after you have visited some splendid places in Spiti and Bhutan. However, there was this one moment where monks were humming some mantra in perfect sync creating a congruous symphony that made the disappointment vanish for a few minutes and after that, well, it was back again!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;image height=&quot;300em&quot; width=&quot;225em&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/mcleo1.jpg&quot;&gt; &lt;/image&gt;
&lt;image height=&quot;300em&quot; width=&quot;375em&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/mcleo2.jpg&quot;&gt; &lt;/image&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  The second day, I again walked down the same path. However this time, the road did not seem fascinating enough. I knew what was coming next and that somewhere took away the key ingredient of uncertainty. Is it always like that? Once you start going through the same path, you start getting used to it and slowly it ceases to excite and surprise you. Or does it depend on the individual? For me, it depends on the situation. But there is no denying that the first time, will always be in the top three!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  I got this unique opportunity to observe certain landmark areas during different times of a day - morning, afternoon, evening and night, because well I had nothing much to do. I believe that if you truly want to experience a place, visit it during all phases of the day. I can bet it on my life that the place will transform into something you had never expected. The colours, the smell, the people and the feeling, everything just switches and each part of the day has its own charm. Some are serene and some are filled with humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel that we Indians never glorify our places and monuments. I remember visiting Lord’s in London. The stadium was not something extra ordinary. You will find similar or better stadiums around the world. But then what was different at Lord’s? The whole experience that they have created makes it royal and grand. The Dharamshala Cricket Stadium is one of the most scenic cricket stadiums in the world, but we never create that kind of experience around it. The stadium looked pale and lonely with just the Dhauladhar range trying to make up for the bland surroundings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;image height=&quot;300em&quot; width=&quot;275em&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/mcleo3.jpg&quot;&gt; &lt;/image&gt;
&lt;image height=&quot;300em&quot; width=&quot;375em&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/mcleo4.jpg&quot;&gt; &lt;/image&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my second and the last day, I was sitting in this cosy little cafe in Mcleodganj, reading Kafka on the Shore with slow moving clouds in front of my eyes. I sat there for around four hours. When travelling alone, there will be times, especially near the end of your trip, when you would yearn to have someone with you. You start to regret for not have planned the trip to perfection. And the most difficult part is shaking those thoughts because they will come for sure. I had those exact same thoughts in that cafe, but the book, the view and the hot ginger lemon slowly erased those thoughts out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt; And I love living,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;और मैं जी रहा हूँ |&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Aug 2017 18:43:39 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/travel/solo-trip-dharamshala-mcleodganj</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/travel/solo-trip-dharamshala-mcleodganj</guid>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why to keep a log file and how to keep it in R?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the first things we are taught in Programming 101 is to write a well structured &amp;amp; commented code. And as any newbie would, we ignore this lesson and focus on achieving the end result. Continuing the same learnings, I coded a R(the R language!) script to be run on files amounting to 30GBs! This was my first professional experience after my graduation and I did not want to fuck up. So, I structured the code, wrote all the comments and ran it on all the files. And what happened next?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All files were not structured the same way and so my script broke for a few files, leaving my final dataset void of some very important data. Moreover, my script was deleting some rows from every file, and thus again I was tampering with the original dataset without any logical and concrete reason behind it. It might not sound something as significant as not achieving the final goal, but believe me, in &lt;em&gt;data science if your data is not representative of the true dataset, your analysis is considered void.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Log file is a file that records events that occur during a process. It basically helps to track back the process and discover if anything has gone wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reasons to keep a Log File&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how to account for such cases? &lt;em&gt;Maintain a Log File&lt;/em&gt;! If you need more reasons for maintaining a log file, here are few I can think of -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Large datasets follow Murphy’s Law. &lt;em&gt;Anything that can go wrong, will go wrong.&lt;/em&gt; And log file is the best way to keep a check&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;While running a common script on several multiple files, log file will give you a gist of the whole process&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Log file will help for future reference, for your own self and also for others who will use the script or the dataset again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What to write in a log file?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, okay! I know log file is important, but what do I write in the log file? &lt;em&gt;It depends on the use case.&lt;/em&gt; As someone who works with data daily, I usually maintain the following parameters in my log file -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Total number of Files the script was run for&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;File names&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Number of rows in each file (before and after processing)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Number of Columns in each file (before and after processing)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Any specific parameter important to the particular dataset&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Processing time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to keep a log file in R?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;createLog&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;log_con&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;file&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;process.log&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;open&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;w&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;nrow&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;file&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;log_con&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sep&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;se&quot;&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a very basic way to keep a log file. I prefer using this function in every script because it gives me the freedom to choose the contents of my log file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy Coding!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jul 2017 01:43:39 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/datascience/why-to-keep-a-logfile</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/datascience/why-to-keep-a-logfile</guid>
        
        
        <category>datascience</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>When Breath Becomes Air - Paul Kalanithi</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I have never been a big fan of memoirs or biographies. However, Bill Gate’s on Paul Kalanithi’s autobiography motivated me to give this genre a try. I remember picking up this book on a train journey, and finishing it in one go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Death is never easy, especially when you know it is coming. Paul, a young ambitious surgeon who was at his peak, suddenly finds out that he is diagnosed with terminal cancer. When breath becomes Air, is the journey from this realization to his very last breath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What happened to Paul was tragic, but he was not a tragedy.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are basically two different sets of experiences that the author goes through - one, is how he being a doctor takes on the challenge of being a patient and two, is the obvious personal and professional trauma he and his family undergoes. The author also shares his view on faith &amp;amp; science and how he distinguishes between them. Those thoughts would not be as impactful as they would seem when supplemented with the raw &amp;amp; blunt writing of Paul Kalanithi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally found the whole narration of his residency days a bit boring and lengthy. However, that very part gave an inside look to the surgeon side of the author, which in retrospect becomes very important to understand the whole story. Paul’s motivation and strength to write this book in the middle of all the pains of chemo-therapy is highly commendable. But I guess, writing was always Paul’s first love and he died doing what he loved the most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not know this person before reading this book and neither did I search about him after reading it. But the kind of impact his words and his thoughts create is boundless. I am sure Paul would not have liked to make his book a synonym for death and tragedy. Read it to understand a magnificent man who lived the best he could, and at the end that is what really matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am sure I will pick this book again. This book has so branches of meanings that you ought to discover new ones when you read it again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was the life he was given, and this is what he made of it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the highlighted lines which I totally fell in love with  -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the unexamined life was not worth living, was the unlived life worth examining?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You could not help but feel your specklike existence against the immensity of the mountain, the earth, the universe, and yet still feel your own two feet on the talus, reaffirming your presence amid the grandeur.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I don’t believe in the wisdom of children, nor in the wisdom of the old. There is a moment, a cusp, when the sum of gathered experience is worn down by the details of living. We are never so wise as when we live in this moment.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Looking out over the expanse ahead I saw not an empty wasteland but something simpler: a blank page on which I would go on.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can’t ever reach perfection, but you can believe in an asymptote toward which you are ceaselessly striving.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When you come to one of the many moments in life where you must give an account of yourself, provide a ledger of what you have been, and done, and meant to the world, do not, I pray, discount that you filled a dying man’s days with a sated joy, a joy unknown to me in all my prior years, a joy that does not hunger for more and more but rests, satisfied. In this time, right now, that is an enormous thing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Although these last few years have been wrenching and difficult—sometimes almost impossible—they have also been the most beautiful and profound of my life, requiring the daily act of holding life and death, joy and pain in balance and exploring new depths of gratitude and love.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(I have a long list of highlights, do ping me if you want to read them.)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jul 2017 19:43:39 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/books/when-breath-becomes-air</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/books/when-breath-becomes-air</guid>
        
        
        <category>books</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>And We Part</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;And then we left for our own ways, just like we had come together after walking our own path on that sunny July 21st morning. Who knew, these four years will make us into friends, enemies, partners in crime, shoulders to cry on, faces we despise, but at the end, these very same people will make us cry while bidding our final goodbyes.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always disliked endings. Whether it was when I completed a great book , a high school farewell or an end to a memorable trip, it was always tough. This is one of such moments, where everything I knew, everything I was a part of, and everything that has shaped me into “me” is coming to an end. I am separating from a place which was &lt;em&gt;“my home more than my home”&lt;/em&gt; for four years.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;image src=&quot;/assets/images/farewell.jpg&quot;&gt; &lt;/image&gt;

&lt;p&gt; There have been countless memories we have shared, but the foremost thing I will miss for the years to come are the people I met here. &lt;em&gt;Seniors who guided us, classmates who walked with us &amp;amp; juniors who made our experiences worth sharing.&lt;/em&gt; It is amusing how I have stored all names in my phone with IITJ behind them. But the fact is, there is no need of an “IITJ” to remind me who these people are. Not even in my wildest dream can I forget these people, or confuse them with others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is only when you are about to lose something, do you realise its true value in life. These past weeks have been emotionally toiling, to say the least. You get a strange feeling when you are about to leave a place. Like you’ll not only miss the people you love but you’ll miss the person you are now at this time and this place, because you will never be this way ever again. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ujjwal Anand beautifully summed up my emotions today -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Doesn’t matter how hard you try, if you have the guts to build a friendship this strong, have the balls to face the tears, cause they will come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, as I glance at that GPRA gate for the last time wiping those tears, myriad of memories flash across my mind. Today, a part of me dies. A part that will always be remembered, but which can never be resurrected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fare Thee Well IITJ! Fare Thee Well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UG201313015 signing off.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2017 18:43:39 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/randomblog/and-we-part</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/randomblog/and-we-part</guid>
        
        
        <category>randomblog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Podcast #2 - Startify : The Journey of Student Entrepreneurs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Startify has been one of the best decisions of my undergraduate life. We got this idea of documenting our journey in
a form of a podcast when we were traveling with our E-Cell juniors. We had real fun while making this. Enjoy the
conversation!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This podcast revolves around three IIT undergrad students, who took the leap and started up Startify in their sophomore year. Startify is basically an online incubation hub which helps startup grow. Startify has been acquired by an incubator based out of Jaipur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The podcast is in the form of a story - right from how the founders met, ideated, to how they got their first customer and the much famous exit. The founders have tried to share their learnings at every juncture of their journey. Part 1 of the podcast is more fun and less knowledge, but as you go further into the second part, the story becomes more exciting with some pointed takeaways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shout out to Abhinav, Karthik and E-Cell IIT Jodhpur for all the help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who prefer downloading podcasts - &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/startify_podcast&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Visit this link &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;120&quot; src=&quot;https://www.mixcloud.com/widget/iframe/?feed=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.mixcloud.com%2Fachyut-joshi%2Fpodcast-2-part-l-startify-the-journey-of-student-entrepreneurs%2F&amp;amp;hide_cover=1&amp;amp;light=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;120&quot; src=&quot;https://www.mixcloud.com/widget/iframe/?feed=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.mixcloud.com%2Fachyut-joshi%2Fpodcast-2-part-ll-startify-the-journey-of-student-entrepreneurs%2F&amp;amp;hide_cover=1&amp;amp;light=1&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2017 00:43:39 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/podcast/podcast-2-startify-journey-of-student-entrepreneurs</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/podcast/podcast-2-startify-journey-of-student-entrepreneurs</guid>
        
        
        <category>podcast</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Podcast #1 - What If</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I always wanted to record a podcast of my own. And finally, after many failed attempts, we recorded this
when we had gone out for a dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This podcast basically consists of three final year undergraduate students(one of them is obviously me), contemplating on their journey so far. We discussed a hypothetical situation where we were guaranteed our dream career on the first day of
college, and then how this would have changed our stay at IIT Jodhpur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is our first podcast, so I am certain that there are several mistakes. However, we enjoyed as hell while making it, and I am sure you will do too, when you hear the conversation. We are waiting for your reviews!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/314453779&amp;amp;color=ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&quot;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 26 Mar 2017 00:43:39 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/podcast/podcast-1-what-if</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/podcast/podcast-1-what-if</guid>
        
        
        <category>podcast</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
