<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Achyut Joshi</title>
    <description>Entrepreneur, Avid Traveller, IITian, Skeptic, Hustler and a lifelong learner. I share my life through this blog.
</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2016 18:14:42 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2016 18:14:42 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to run automated python scripts on remote machines</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I am currently working on the B.Tech Project that involves predicting flight prices. To build the models, I needed historical flight prices. Unfortunately, such data is not available and so I had to build a scraper to extract flight prices daily and save it in a csv file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building a scraper is no rocket science. If you are using python, there are multiple frameworks like Scrapy, which are very powerful tools. My particular problem was not a complex one, and therefore I manually built a script which extracts the useful fields from Makemytrip website. You can look at the code &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/achyutjoshi/Flight-Prices-Scraper&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the most challenging part of this whole process was to schedule it. I wanted my script to run on a particular time, daily and everytime it runs, it should append the values to the original csv file. Scheduling it on my local machine was not a solution, because I cannot keep it running all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had two options -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Run it on my institute’s server&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use virtual machines provided by &lt;a href=&quot;http://azure.microsoft.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Microsoft Azure&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://aws.amazon.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;AWS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to some reason, the institute’s server was not responding. So the next best possible option was to use Microsoft Azure. AWS is better with respect to performance, but you need to be technically very sound to set up the server using AWS.So, I setup a virtual machine using the least possible configuration on Azure. It provides us with a INR 12k free credits on signing up. I used SSH to login into my remote system and installed python and all the libraries that were needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linux system provides a beautiful option called Cronjobs. It is an in-built scheduling option that is very easy to use. The major problem you can face when scheduling your scripts is the permissions of the file. Do make sure that you have given execution rights to all users(to be on the safer side). Also, if your script is writing/reading a file, make sure those files have the respective permissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the few links that will help you to setup a cronjob and run a python script -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adminschoice.com/crontab-quick-reference&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Quick Reference&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/8727935/execute-python-script-on-crontab&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Stack OverFlow - Python Script&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, data science frequently requires the tedious job of collecting data. However, if you just learn the basics of scraping and scheduling scripts on a remote machine, your life will be a lot more easier.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2016 00:43:39 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/datascience/how-to-run-automated-python-script-on-remote-machine</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/datascience/how-to-run-automated-python-script-on-remote-machine</guid>
        
        
        <category>datascience</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>One Hot Encoding in Data Science</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I consider myself a newbie for the data analysis world. What I have understood so far is that data preparation is the most important step while solving any problem. Each predictive  model requires a certain type of data and in a certain way. For instance, tree based boosting models like xgboost require all the feature variables to be numeric. While solving the San Francisco Crime Classification problem on Kaggle, I stumbled upon different ways to handle categorical variables. One of the method to convert a categorical input variable into a continuous one is One Hot Encoding/ Dummy coding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many a times we have categorical variables with many levels. For example in the SF Crime Classification problem, there were 39 different levels of crime. Now many learning algorithms either learn a single weight per feature, or they use distances between samples. In both cases having a categorical variable with more levels will decrease the accuracy of the model. Let us look into both cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Linear Model&lt;/strong&gt; :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose you have a dataset having only a single categorical feature “colour”, with values “Blue”, “Green” and “Red”. Assume, that these are encoded as 0, 1 and 2. You then have a weight w for this feature in a linear classifier, which will make some kind of decision based on the constraint w×x + b &amp;gt; 0, or equivalently w×x &amp;lt; b.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem now is that the weight w cannot encode a three-way choice. The three possible values of w×x are 0, w and 2×w. Either these three all lead to the same decision (they’re all &amp;lt; b or ≥b) or “Blue” and “Green” lead to the same decision, or “Green” and “Red” give the same decision. There’s no possibility for the model to learn that “Blue” and “Red” should be given the same label, with “French” the odd one out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dummy coding will convert this colour feature into three features – ‘isgreen’ ‘isred’ and ‘isblue. By this, we effectively blow up the feature space to three features, which will each get their own weights, so the decision function is now w[Blue]x[Blue] + w[Green]x[Green] + w[Red]x[Red] &amp;lt; b, where all the x’s are booleans. This easily caters the problem we were having before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distance-Based&lt;/strong&gt; :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, any learner based on standard distance metrics (such as k-nearest neighbors) between samples will get confused without one-hot encoding. With the naive encoding and Euclidean distance, the distance between Green and Red is 1. The distance between Red and Blue is 2. But with the one-hot encoding, the pairwise distances between [1, 0, 0], [0, 1, 0] and [0, 0, 1] are all equal to √2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this is not true for all models. Decision trees and derived models such as random forests, if deep enough, can handle categorical variables without one-hot encoding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other Methods used for Encoding&lt;/strong&gt; –&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ordinal Coding – Assign Numbers to each categories&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Binary: first the categories are encoded as ordinal, then those integers are converted into binary code, then the digits from that binary string are split into separate columns.  This encodes the data in fewer dimensions that one-hot, but with some distortion of the distances.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References: Quora &amp;amp; Analytics Vidya&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2016 00:43:39 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/datascience/one-hot-encoding</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/datascience/one-hot-encoding</guid>
        
        
        <category>datascience</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What I learnt by speaking in front of 120 school kids</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After a long long time, today when I entered the auditorium of MPS Jodhpur (a school in Jodhpur) I started missing my school again. As we grow up, we begin to get indifferent to things from our past. But that auditorium, those young kids in uniform and those teachers shouting at them to shut up, brought back happy memories from my Vidyani days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;image src=&quot;/assets/images/mps1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/image&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were invited by the school administration to give a two-hour talk on engineering, entrepreneurship and basic motivation. Having an experience of giving talks many times, this particular event was special for us. It was the first time we spoke in front of school kids. We had brainstormed a lot and tried to find out ingenious ways of presenting in front of these young lads. The key hurdle was to guess their level of understanding and intelligence. We as college students tend to take certain things for granted which are not very obvious at a school level. But somehow we managed and it was a hell of an event!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So as soon as we entered the auditorium, the students started to gaze at us as if we were some aliens. Remember the times when we as school kids used to gossip and stare at anyone who is new? Being at the other end of the dais made me realise how creepy we used to be! We were felicitated by the Headmistress of the school and then were invited to start our talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;image src=&quot;/assets/images/mps2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/image&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The talk consisted of us telling our stories and sharing our regrets with the students. It was mainly ‘gyaan’ and more importantly, we had to put it in a way that they can relate to. Slowly as we progressed, surprisingly and to our amazement, those students opened up and started to ask some beguiling doubts. We were startled by their level of knowledge, enthusiasm and the curiosity to know things. They knew the basic mechanisms of a business including marketing, sales, product development and funding! Things which I personally learnt only after getting into college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever Himanshu (the other person who was speaking with me) spoke, I intently watched how the students reacted. The way they were looking up to us and expecting something great from us made me realise how influential we can be. As seniors, we have the power to mould them in the best way possible and as one of the teachers of the school put it, “Students can easily connect with people of similar ages!”. Whenever they got a chance, they used to jump out of their seat and come running to us with all sort of questions and believe me it is very difficult to convince a 16- year old school kid who won’t leave you unless he has a perfect answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;image src=&quot;/assets/images/mps3.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/image&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when we were walking out of the room after our talk, everyone in the room started clapping. In that one moment, one small moment, I lived one of the best times in my life. It feels satisfying to see that you caused a change in someone’s life. We were again felicitated in the principal’s office and were offered with snacks(a big thing for any hosteler!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even while I am writing this, I received a mail from one of the students seeking my advice. That is enough to prove that we succeeded in our endeavour in some small way. The whole experience was rejuvenating, nostalgic and enlightening to say the least. This day will certainly be remembered for a long time to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;image src=&quot;/assets/images/mps4.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/image&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Apr 2016 18:43:39 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/randomblog/what-i-learnt-by-speaking-to-school-kids</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/randomblog/what-i-learnt-by-speaking-to-school-kids</guid>
        
        
        <category>randomblog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>I Failed</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I had written in my earlier post, that I would become an early riser this year. I tried and I failed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been 2 months and 21 days and I am ashamed to share that I woke up early only for 23 days. It doesn’t mean that I hated waking up early, I loved it. The serenity, the calmness and the solitude was addictive, but it wasn’t addictive enough to wake an lazy ass like me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried many things. I read a lot. I made a morning routine. I applied all the technicalities of making a habit as explained by Charles Duhigg. I spent an hour identifying the cues and rewards and made a 15-day plan for the same. I followed it for some days and then I just stopped. Meditating in the morning was refreshing and so was exercising and drinking a cup of warm lemon water. Yet I couldn’t continue it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole experiment made me to doubt myself. I had always thought myself to be someone who cannot persist with one thing. And this whole incident proved it to me. It is very agonizing to know your mistakes and yet be helpless to solve it. The failure may be due to the fact that my schedule is unpredictable. Whatever may it be, one thing I know for sure – I failed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, for the time being, I quit and I no longer will be trying to wake up early. I will come back to it, once I finish with my engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS. I have my whole experiment documented. If anyone wants to try it, I will be more than happy to share!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2016 18:43:39 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/randomblog/i-failed</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/randomblog/i-failed</guid>
        
        
        <category>randomblog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Kasol : A place closest to Heaven</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I woke up to the roller-coaster ride of our Himachal State Transport bus when it reached Bhunter(a small town before Manali). Last night was tough after being stalled at Ambala Cant for more than 4 hours waiting for our bus to which we finally gave up and boarded the local state transport bus. But as soon as we got down at Bhunter, the cold air brought a sense of freshness in our bodies. We had to search out our bags for warm clothes because it was damn cold. We looked somewhat like this –&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;image src=&quot;/assets/images/kasol1.jpg&quot;&gt; &lt;/image&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kasol was still an hour ride from Bhunter. You ditch the Manali road and follow the Parvati for an hour, on a life-threatening road full of turns and zig-zags. Reaching Kasol after a unvarying drive, I was in a tizzy, partly out of hunger and partly out of the happy Himalayan wind.  The moment we reached Kasol, we saw a bunch of hippies strolling down the narrow roads of Kasol evidently making most of the moment. The red-and-white mobile telephony tower stands right at the edge of the river that divides Old Kasol and New Kasol. There is a bridge in the middle of the town and a few restaurants here and there, but that is all. The main beauty of this infamous town lies within, and you had to explore to find it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;image src=&quot;/assets/images/kasol2.jpg&quot;&gt; &lt;/image&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We headed straight to the riverside to catch River Parvati wildly flapping its way across this tiny Himalayan village. The Sun was just coming out. A dog was crossing the river on an old, rickety bridge(which also led straight to the party town – Chalal). There was wind in my hair and I was content in that one moment of awe. We sat there, looking at each other and then gazing upon the backdrop of the Himalayas. Trust me, 5 childhood friends meeting after a long time could feel the intensity of this moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;image src=&quot;/assets/images/kasol3.jpg&quot;&gt; &lt;/image&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The subtle moment was disturbed by our crave for rest. Some hours of sleep was enough to get us back in action mode. As such there are not many things to do in Kasol. You could either trek to Malana, Tosh or KheerGanga. But for the first evening, we chose to sit ideally near the riverbanks and just breathe. There are many good places to eat, like a good breakfast at German Bakery or a finger licking meal at Little Italy. At night, we headed out to Chalal to experience the much talked about party in the valley. Because it was the last few hours of the party, we somehow sneaked in and danced to a few last songs. The trail back to our rooms was in total darkness, walking side by side river Parvati to guide us. It seemed quite ironic to be guided by the gregarious river when we are the ones to pollute it in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;image src=&quot;/assets/images/kasol4.jpg&quot;&gt; &lt;/image&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day, we trekked to Manikaran which turned out to be a sacred place for the Sikhs. A word of caution, there are very few ATMs in this area and unfortunately not all work every time. So carry enough cash always. Then we took a detour and climbed a mountain which seemed accessible from the banks of the gurudwara. But as we kept on climbing, the peak seemed to be mocking us by getting higher and higher. In the end, as it always turns out Nature won. But the view was enthralling and worth every drop of sweat spent for climbing up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;image src=&quot;/assets/images/kasol5.jpg&quot;&gt; &lt;/image&gt;
&lt;image src=&quot;/assets/images/kasol6.jpg&quot;&gt; &lt;/image&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone has a different kind of tale to tell when they visit Kasol. We had a tale of nostalgia, we had some stories of the past to remember and a promise of making many more. Kasol helps you to slow down a bit in this fast paced world, slow down and be grateful for every tiny little thing. It is not just a place on the map, it is that tranquillity that comes with your eyes sparkling every time you see the starlit night sky or with the way you open up with your best friends and relive the younger carefree days. It forces you to do certain things which will stay as a lasting memory of the trip. There was indeed something different in that place which makes us crave to experience it once again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;image src=&quot;/assets/images/kasol7.jpg&quot;&gt; &lt;/image&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2016 18:43:39 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/travel/kasol-place-closest-to-heaven</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/travel/kasol-place-closest-to-heaven</guid>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
