<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Achyut Joshi</title>
    <description>Entrepreneur, Avid Traveller, IITian, Skeptic, Hustler and a lifelong learner. I share my life through this blog.
</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2017 15:00:22 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2017 15:00:22 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Powerpoints - How not to make them?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;PowerPoint was developed by engineers as a tool to help them communicate in a better way. The programmers behind PowerPoint saw it as a clever hack—a way to save time and money instead of creating slides the old fashioned way. It is an amazing tool for presenting your ideas in a way that the audience can relate to! However, we, the users, have made a complete mockery of presentations. To a certain extent, Microsoft is to blame for the dismal built-in wizards, templates and clip-arts - those hideous Microsoft creations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have noticed some abysmal design mistakes in various powerpoints. Some of them which can be easily prevented are -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Text Too Small&lt;/strong&gt; - Before deciding on the text size of your content, you should understand the size of the audience and the room you will be presenting it. Change your font size accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dreadful colour schemes&lt;/strong&gt; - There is no point of your powerpoint if your colour scheme sucks and as a result, no one is able to understand the slides.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Too many bullet points&lt;/strong&gt; - Bullet points are supposed to be used to communicate important points. Never use them in excess otherwise they lose the importance&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bad selection of fonts&lt;/strong&gt; - Being a novice designer myself, there are no words through which I can emphasize the importance of fonts. I spend at least 30 minutes to decide my fonts.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Videos and Audios never work&lt;/strong&gt; - Embedded videos and audios don’t work most of the time. Moreover, they break the flow of your presentation. Play them either at the end or at the start. Avoid them in the middle of your presentation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Too many slide transitions &amp;amp; animations&lt;/strong&gt; - They do more bad than good. These can get rather tiring on the audience and thus keep the powerpoint simple.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reading off each word&lt;/strong&gt; - Did your audience really have to come all this way to a meeting to listen to you read the slides? Why not just send them over? Never, just never make this mistake!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one underlying fact every one of us should understand is - &lt;em&gt;presentations are made to make communication seamless and easy.&lt;/em&gt; Therefore before presenting, take a moment and imagine yourself as the audience and ask the question - “Will this powerpoint aid me to understand the idea better?”. If you have even a 5% of doubt, change the powerpoint!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As Seth Godin rightly points out, Communication is the transfer of emotion. Communication is about getting others to adopt your point of view, to help them understand why you’re excited (or sad, or optimistic or whatever else you are.) PowerPoint presents an amazing opportunity. You can use the screen to talk emotionally to the audience’s right brain (through their eyes), and your words can go through the audience’s ears to talk to their left brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certain Pointers that will help you become a better presenter -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cue Cards&lt;/strong&gt; -  Make yourself a cue card for each slide. It should cover all the points that you want to make and thus these cards will provide a basic framework and storyline for your presentation&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Slides to aid your words&lt;/strong&gt; - Make slides that reinforce your words, not repeat them&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Leave-behind&lt;/strong&gt; - Create a printed document which works as a summary of your content and give it to your audience after you have finished with your presentation&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No more than &lt;strong&gt;six words on a slide&lt;/strong&gt;. EVER.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10/20/30 Rule&lt;/strong&gt; -  It recommends limiting the number of your slides to 10 and your presentation time to 20 minutes but using at least a 30-point font size.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will find many such hacks and rules that provide you with a framework to make the most from your powerpoint presentation. However, you will have to decide your own rules suiting your style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, PowerPoints and other presentation tools are visual aids. You want to connect how your slide looks to what you’re saying and present it in a form of a story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The home run is easy to describe: You put up a slide. It triggers an emotional reaction in the audience. They sit up and want to know what you’re going to say that fits in with that image. Then, if you do it right, every time they think of what you said, they’ll see the image (and vice versa).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Useful Links -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fonts - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2011/07/best-free-fonts-designers/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.entrepreneur.com/article/238243&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Design - &lt;a href=&quot;http://lifehacker.com/5821548/dos-and-donts-of-making-awesome-diagrams-for-slides&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Templates - Visit slideshare, you will find some real-life designs&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 11 Feb 2017 03:43:39 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/randomblog/powerpoints</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/randomblog/powerpoints</guid>
        
        
        <category>randomblog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Power of Habit by Charles Duhigg</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In Power of Habit, the author examines why some people and companies struggle to change, despite years of trying, while other seem to remake themselves overnight. The book is divided into three sections, namely Individual, Company and Societies. The author discusses how habits are formed in all three areas with some compelling evidences. Personally, I have always disliked self-help books due to the sole reason of them being boring. But surprisingly, Charles Duhigg has found an interesting way to present boring tips through this best-seller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part A – Individual Habits&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ch- 1  The Habit Loop:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we picture our brain as an onion, composed of layers of cells, then the outside layers – those closest to the scalp – are generally the most recent additions from an evolutionary perspective. Deep inside is where automatic behaviours occur. One such part of the brain – basal ganglia, controls habit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process in which the brain converts a sequence of actions into the an automatic routine is known as chunking and it is at the root of habit formation. Examples of behavioral chunks –  You automatically putting toothpaste on toothbrush before putting it into your mouth. Habits emerge because the brain in constantly looking for ways to save effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Habit process within our brain is a three-step loop. First, there is a cue, a trigger that tells your brain to go to automatic mode and which habit to use. Then there is routine, which can be physical or mental or emotional. Finally , there is a reward, which helps your brain figure out if this particular loop is worth remembering for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ch-2 The Craving Brain (How to create new habits)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example of Pepsodent – How Hopkins made Americans develop the habit of brushing in the morning(a way to advertise Pepsodent). How ever complex the whole idea seems, everything burns down to three things – cue, routine, reward. He learned the right human psychology which was grounded in two basic rules – Find a simple and obvious cue and second clearly define the rewards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prof Wolfram Schultz conducted a few experiments on monkeys to know the inner workings of the brain during the habit loop. He found out that once the habit has been created, the monkeys craved of the rewards, and when they didn’t arrive, they began to go mad. Therefore, habits are very powerful: they create neurological cravings. Most of the time, these cravings emerge so gradually that we are not really aware they exist. But as we associate cues with certain reward, a subconscious craving emerges in our brains that start the habit loop spinning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way new habits are created – by putting together a cue, a routine and a reward, and then cultivating a craving that drives the loop. The cue in addition to triggering a routine must also trigger a craving for the reward to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consumers need some kind of signal that a product is working. For instance, all toothpaste have a cool tinge irrespective of the flavour. This cool tinge does not help in cleaning our teeth, rather they leave behind a cool effect which indirectly makes us believe that the tooth-paste has done its job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ch-3 The Golden Rule of Habit Change&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example of Tony Dungy and his rugby team – Tony Dungy’s coaching philosophy was that the key to winning was changing player’s habits. He wanted players to stop making so many decisions during the game. He wanted them to react automatically, habitually. Dungy only wanted to target the middle step – routine. It is easier to convince someone to adopt a new behaviour if there was something familiar at the beginning and end.To change a habit, you must keep the old cue and reward and but change the routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example of Alcoholics Anonymous – AA forces addicts to identify the cues and the rewards that encourage their alcoholic habits, and then helps them find new behaviours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To change an old habit, you have to target the old craving. You have to keep the same cues and rewards as before and feed the craving by inserting a new routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However even if you give people better habits, it doesn’t repair why they started drinking in the first place. Eventually, they will have a bad day and no new routine is going to make everything seem okay. What can make a difference is believing that they can cope with that stress without alcohol. People might be skeptical about their ability to change if they are by themselves, but a group will convince them to suspend disbelief. A community creates belief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Habits are most malleable when the Golden Rule of Habit is applied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PART B – Organisations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ch -4 Keystone Habits&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example – Alcoa and its CEO Paul O’Neill – O’Neill believed that some habits have the power to start a chain reaction, changing other habits as they move through an organisation. Some habits matter more than others in remaking businesses and lives. These are called “Key Stone Habits”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keystone habits say that success doesn’t depend on getting every single thing right, but instead relies on identifying a few key priorities and fashioning them into powerful levers. Individuals have habits and organisations have routines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To bring Alcoa back on track, O’Neill figured out his top priority would be something that everyone – unions and executives- could agree was important. He needed a focus that would bring people together, that would give him leverage to change how people worked and communicated. He chose Safety! The key to protecting Alcoa employees was understanding why injuries happened. And to understand the why you had to study how the process was going wrong. To understand how things were going wrong, you had to bring in people who could educate about quality control and safety. In short, to protect the workers, Alcoa needed to become the best, most streamlined aluminum company on earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you focus on changing or cultivating keystone habits, you can cause widespread shifts. Keystone habits offer what is known within academic literature as “small wins”. They help other habits to flourish by creating new structures, and they establish cultures where change becomes contagious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example – Michael Phelps – Phelps’s coach, Bowman believed that key to victory was creating right routines. All he needed to do was target few specific habits that had nothing to do with swimming and everything to do with creating right mindset. Bowman would tell Phelps to go home and “watch the video-tape, which was a mental visualization of a perfect race, before he goes to sleep and when he wakes up”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once a small win has been accomplished, forces are set in motion that favour another small win. Small wins fuel transformative changes by leveraging tiny advantages into patterns that convince people that bigger achievements are within reach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ch – 5  When Willpower becomes Automatic&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example – Starbucks – Starbucks teach their employees via classroom sessions the basic methods and ways to deal with a Starbucks customer. At the core of the education is an intense focus on an all important habit : willpower. Willpower is the single most important keystone habit for individual success. The best way to strengthen willpower is to make it into a habit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Willpower isn’t just a skill. It is a muscle, and it gets tired as it works harder.  If you want to do something that requires willpower, you have to conserve your willpower till that time of the day. As people strengthen their willpower in one part of their lives, that strength spilled over into other things and touched everything. Good habits spill over into other parts of lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Starbucks LATTE method – We Listen to the customer, Acknowledge their complaint, Take action by solving the problem, Thank them and then Explain why the problem occurred. This is how willpower becomes a habit – by choosing a certain behavior ahead of time, and then following that routine when an inflection point arrives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parents should ask such questions to help their children learn how to set goals – “How are you going to study tonight”, “What are you going to do tomorrow”,  “How do you know you are ready for the tests?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When people are asked to do something that takes self-control, if they think they are doing it for personal reasons – if they feel it’s like a choice or something that they enjoy because it helps someone else – it’s much less taxing. If they feel like they have no autonomy, their willpower muscles get tired much faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply giving employees a sense of agency – a feeling that they are in control, that they have actual decision-making control – can radically increase how much energy and focus they bring to their jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ch – 6 Power of Crisis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no organisations without institutional habits. There are only places where they are deliberately designed, and places where they are created without forethought. Sometimes in the heat of a crisis, the right habits emerge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nelson and Winter’s theories – Much of firm behavior is best understood as a reflection of general habits and strategic orientations coming from the firm’s past rather than the result of a detailed survey of remote twigs of decision tree. Firms are guided by long-held organisational habits, patterns that often emerge from thousand of employees’ independent decisions. The organizational habits or routines provide hundred of unwritten rules that companies need to operate. They allow workers to experiment with new ideas without having to ask for permission at every step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important benefits of routines is that they create truces between potential warring groups or individuals within an organisation. Organisational routines provide a basic promise – if everyone follows the established patterns and abide by the truce, then rivalries won’t destroy the company, the profits will roll in and eventually everyone will get rich. For an organisation to work, leaders must cultivate habits that both create a real and balanced peace and, paradoxically make it absolutely clear who’s in charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good leaders seize crises to remake organisational habits. A company with dysfunctional habits can’t turn around simply because a leader orders it. Rather, wise executives seek out moments of crisis- or create the perception of crisis- and cultivate the sense that something must change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ch 7- How Target knows what you want before you do&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consumers act like creatures of habit, automatically repeating past behaviors with little regard to current goals. Yet each person’s habits are different. People’s buying habits are more likely to change when they go through a major life event. And the biggest change is having a baby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is evidence that a preference for that thing that sound familiar is a product of our neurology. Listening habits allow us to unconsciously separate important noises from those that can’t be ignored. Radio listeners didn’t want to make a conscious decision each time they were presented with a new song. Instead, their brains wanted to follow a habit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listeners are happy to sit through a song they might dislike as long as it seems something they have heard before. Pregnant women are happy to use coupons they receive in the mail unless those coupons make it obvious that Target is spying on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“By dressing something new in old clothes, and making the unfamiliar seem familiar” – the golden rule for making your product viral. How to do this? Sandwich theorem – Sandwich the unfamiliar between the familiar. If you dress something new in old habits, it is easier for the public to accept it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part – C Habits of Societies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social habits are what fill streets who may not know one another, who are marching for different reasons, but who are all moving in the same direction. A movement starts because of Social habits of friendship and strong ties between close acquaintances. It grows because of habits of community, and the weak ties that hold neighbourhoods and clans together. And it endures because leaders give participants new habits that create a fresh sense of identity and a feeling of ownership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For an idea to grow beyond a community, it must become self-propelling. And the surest way to achieve that is to give people new habits that help them figure out where to go on their own. The will to believe is the most important ingredient in creating belief in change. And that one of the most important methods for creating that belief was habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FRAMEWORK to create or change Habits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identify the routine&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Experiment with rewards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Isolate the cue&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have a plan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 11 Feb 2017 01:43:39 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/reviews/power-of-habit</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/reviews/power-of-habit</guid>
        
        
        <category>reviews</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What After Graduation?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One of my major goals of 2016 was to inch closer to a particular career path that I will embark on after I graduate. However, like all new year goals, I am not even close to deciding what I want to do after I finish by B.Tech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These four years of college have been enlightening in many ways but unlike many of my batchmates, I have grown more confused about my future. There are infinite opportunities out there and with a tad bit of experience I have eliminated some and confused between some.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MBA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before my summer internship with Accenture, I was certain about MBA and even had started preparing for CAT. However, the two months made me realise that I was not yet ready to pull out from the technical world. Coincidentally, I was introduced to data analytics by a friend and as I dug deeper into the field, it got enthralling. MBA was eliminated and so enters MS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MS(Master of Science)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In undergraduate coursework, we do not study any dedicated coursework for data analytics. There are only certain introductory courses on probability, database systems and machine learning. Thus a post graduation study becomes mandatory if one seriously wants to go deeper into this particular field. However, in my case, because MS became an option like a bomb, waiting for a year or two to gain some experience in this field and then opting for an MS in data analytics seemed more logical. Thus, MS is also eliminated for the time being(at least for a year or two).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Job Experience&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone with even a two-month industry exposure can bet on his life and tell that the undergraduate coursework and actual industry implementation are two different worlds. No doubt, the coursework and the projects help in the process of completing a job but the whole experience is divergent. Therefore, right now, getting a job experience seems to be the best and the safest option. Apart from earning some money, it will also provide with a good technical exposure in data analytics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there is a twist in this story too! Working with a startup and working for a big multi-national serves two totally different objectives. Generally speaking, a startup is a more unstable, risky and yet more satisfying, challenging &amp;amp; developing option. Personally, having secured a job at Accenture, I am currently hunting for opportunities in a startup and then will decide the best way forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Starting up my own venture&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Startify, my first startup, was a breathtaking experience and once it got acquired my decision to hunt for a job came as a surprise to many. However, to those who know Startify inside out, it would have been very difficult to make Startify profitable &amp;amp; sustainable. Not every startup idea is worth building!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is my belief that an idea originates from a problem and a problem is identified by your surroundings. So, if you get an industry exposure for a few years, you would be exposed to a whole new set of problems, that you wouldn’t have known if you had decided to start right after college.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having said that, there is nothing wrong in starting up right after college if you have found a problem that you are really passionate about. In my case, I have not found that yet and so entrepreneurship is on hold for some time and I am keeping my eyes and ears open to stumble upon a problem that is worth solving for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Young India Fellowship&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got introduced to this particular option by a senior. The Young India Fellowship is basically a one-year multidisciplinary postgraduate diploma programme in Liberal Studies. From the day I read about YIF, it has got me intrigued. &lt;em&gt;YIF will provide a good gap year along with spending a year learning something valuable.&lt;/em&gt; The admission process is very selective and currently, I am waiting for my 2nd round results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I get selected and opt to go forward with joining YIF, it might deviate me from my data analytics track. However, on the other hand, it will give me an opportunity to learn some abstract topics like politics, literature, law &amp;amp; arts and interact with some amazing like-minded people from India. Now, that is some leverage which would be difficult to let go for a person like me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Digital Nomad &amp;amp; Volunteering&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole scene of living among a new culture like Vietnam and along with helping underprivileged children there, exploring and making fascinating memories has always captivated me. Moreover, in this digital world, earning by freelancing is not an impossible task.  Stories of millennials working from the Himalayas and living their dream are very common these days. I have often heard that once we get into the vicious cycle of earning, taking time out for such dreams take impossible courage. &lt;em&gt;Then why not tick off such items from the bucket list right after graduation?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Final Verdict (&lt;em&gt;Never getting there!&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some safe bets, and there are some risky &amp;amp; yet attractive alternatives. On one hand, if I see myself as someone who wants to be a data scientist, taking up a job and then pursuing higher education seems the logical step. However, the hustler inside me prefers taking the risky option of a gap year and trying out new experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2016 15:30:39 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/randomblog/what-after-graduation</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/randomblog/what-after-graduation</guid>
        
        
        <category>randomblog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>It is that time of year again</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It is that time of the year again - the dreaded placements. The same block where once I used to hear noisy birthday bashing or the typical Hindi abuses while playing Counter Strike is now a hostile territory of men at work!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is bloody amusing to find yourself in this very rat race in spite of all the protective shells you try to pretend to wear. There are days where I have nightmares of not getting placed in a good company, or even worse, having my best friends placed and not me. Hell! When did this get so competitive &amp;amp; stressful? But it is actually not our mistake. This is the exact way it has happened in the past, and we will follow it blindly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still remember my JEE preparation days and the same very rat race that I ran. We all were sailing in the same boat. With no clear inclinations towards a field of study or interests, we ran, we ran hard for two long years without looking back with just one goal - IIT. And on the day the result was announced I never felt so empty, with no ambitions &amp;amp; no purpose. But then IIT Jodhpur happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IITs might not be great academically, and especially not IIT Jodhpur, but these 4 years serves you something which might get you back your purpose. Ample of opportunities in the fields you cannot even imagine, friends &amp;amp; seniors who will really sail the world to get you out of trouble and learnings which will stay with you the rest of your life. My three years were something very similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enrolled into a very new branch of Systems Science(even after 3 years, I still don’t know what it is ) in a new IIT. Aspiring to get my branch changed, I studied hard for the first midsem, but soon I came to know I had brilliant classmates, who are more deserving. Since school days I loved programming so I tried competitive programming but soon gave that up too. Then entrepreneurship happened. I got introduced to it by a dear friend, with whom I would end up starting my own venture, and we went crazy. The next two years were energetic, colourful and worth every bit of the hardship. I also got acquainted to data analytics and dived into this field to learn more. In a nutshell, these 3 years I learnt and experienced things that I wouldn’t if I were somewhere else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then it arrived. The fucking fourth and final year. Again it felt like the good old JEE days. Everyone running behind their aims of jobs, masters, MBA etc etc. I am sure many of them are actually interested in whatever they are pursuing, but not me. I have not freaking idea on what I am doing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had promised myself that I won’t run that race again but here I am, reading things for getting a job and spending a good 3-4 hours a day hunting jobs. Why? Do we really need this?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2016 18:43:39 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/randomblog/It-is-that-time-again</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/randomblog/It-is-that-time-again</guid>
        
        
        <category>randomblog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to run automated python scripts on remote machines</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I am currently working on the B.Tech Project that involves predicting flight prices. To build the models, I needed historical flight prices. Unfortunately, such data is not available and so I had to build a scraper to extract flight prices daily and save it in a csv file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building a scraper is no rocket science. If you are using python, there are multiple frameworks like Scrapy, which are very powerful tools. My particular problem was not a complex one, and therefore I manually built a script which extracts the useful fields from Makemytrip website. You can look at the code &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/achyutjoshi/Flight-Prices-Scraper&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the most challenging part of this whole process was to schedule it. I wanted my script to run on a particular time, daily and everytime it runs, it should append the values to the original csv file. Scheduling it on my local machine was not a solution, because I cannot keep it running all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had two options -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Run it on my institute’s server&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use virtual machines provided by &lt;a href=&quot;http://azure.microsoft.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Microsoft Azure&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://aws.amazon.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;AWS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to some reason, the institute’s server was not responding. So the next best possible option was to use Microsoft Azure. AWS is better with respect to performance, but you need to be technically very sound to set up the server using AWS.So, I setup a virtual machine using the least possible configuration on Azure. It provides us with a INR 12k free credits on signing up. I used SSH to login into my remote system and installed python and all the libraries that were needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linux system provides a beautiful option called Cronjobs. It is an in-built scheduling option that is very easy to use. The major problem you can face when scheduling your scripts is the permissions of the file. Do make sure that you have given execution rights to all users(to be on the safer side). Also, if your script is writing/reading a file, make sure those files have the respective permissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the few links that will help you to setup a cronjob and run a python script -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adminschoice.com/crontab-quick-reference&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Quick Reference&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/8727935/execute-python-script-on-crontab&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Stack OverFlow - Python Script&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, data science frequently requires the tedious job of collecting data. However, if you just learn the basics of scraping and scheduling scripts on a remote machine, your life will be a lot more easier.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2016 00:43:39 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/datascience/how-to-run-automated-python-script-on-remote-machine</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/datascience/how-to-run-automated-python-script-on-remote-machine</guid>
        
        
        <category>datascience</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>One Hot Encoding in Data Science</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I consider myself a newbie for the data analysis world. What I have understood so far is that data preparation is the most important step while solving any problem. Each predictive  model requires a certain type of data and in a certain way. For instance, tree based boosting models like xgboost require all the feature variables to be numeric. While solving the San Francisco Crime Classification problem on Kaggle, I stumbled upon different ways to handle categorical variables. One of the method to convert a categorical input variable into a continuous one is One Hot Encoding/ Dummy coding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many a times we have categorical variables with many levels. For example in the SF Crime Classification problem, there were 39 different levels of crime. Now many learning algorithms either learn a single weight per feature, or they use distances between samples. In both cases having a categorical variable with more levels will decrease the accuracy of the model. Let us look into both cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Linear Model&lt;/strong&gt; :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose you have a dataset having only a single categorical feature “colour”, with values “Blue”, “Green” and “Red”. Assume, that these are encoded as 0, 1 and 2. You then have a weight w for this feature in a linear classifier, which will make some kind of decision based on the constraint w×x + b &amp;gt; 0, or equivalently w×x &amp;lt; b.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem now is that the weight w cannot encode a three-way choice. The three possible values of w×x are 0, w and 2×w. Either these three all lead to the same decision (they’re all &amp;lt; b or ≥b) or “Blue” and “Green” lead to the same decision, or “Green” and “Red” give the same decision. There’s no possibility for the model to learn that “Blue” and “Red” should be given the same label, with “French” the odd one out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dummy coding will convert this colour feature into three features – ‘isgreen’ ‘isred’ and ‘isblue. By this, we effectively blow up the feature space to three features, which will each get their own weights, so the decision function is now w[Blue]x[Blue] + w[Green]x[Green] + w[Red]x[Red] &amp;lt; b, where all the x’s are booleans. This easily caters the problem we were having before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distance-Based&lt;/strong&gt; :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, any learner based on standard distance metrics (such as k-nearest neighbors) between samples will get confused without one-hot encoding. With the naive encoding and Euclidean distance, the distance between Green and Red is 1. The distance between Red and Blue is 2. But with the one-hot encoding, the pairwise distances between [1, 0, 0], [0, 1, 0] and [0, 0, 1] are all equal to √2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this is not true for all models. Decision trees and derived models such as random forests, if deep enough, can handle categorical variables without one-hot encoding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other Methods used for Encoding&lt;/strong&gt; –&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ordinal Coding – Assign Numbers to each categories&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Binary: first the categories are encoded as ordinal, then those integers are converted into binary code, then the digits from that binary string are split into separate columns.  This encodes the data in fewer dimensions that one-hot, but with some distortion of the distances.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References: Quora &amp;amp; Analytics Vidya&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2016 00:43:39 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/datascience/one-hot-encoding</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/datascience/one-hot-encoding</guid>
        
        
        <category>datascience</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What I learnt by speaking in front of 120 school kids</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After a long long time, today when I entered the auditorium of MPS Jodhpur (a school in Jodhpur) I started missing my school again. As we grow up, we begin to get indifferent to things from our past. But that auditorium, those young kids in uniform and those teachers shouting at them to shut up, brought back happy memories from my Vidyani days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;image src=&quot;/assets/images/mps1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/image&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were invited by the school administration to give a two-hour talk on engineering, entrepreneurship and basic motivation. Having an experience of giving talks many times, this particular event was special for us. It was the first time we spoke in front of school kids. We had brainstormed a lot and tried to find out ingenious ways of presenting in front of these young lads. The key hurdle was to guess their level of understanding and intelligence. We as college students tend to take certain things for granted which are not very obvious at a school level. But somehow we managed and it was a hell of an event!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So as soon as we entered the auditorium, the students started to gaze at us as if we were some aliens. Remember the times when we as school kids used to gossip and stare at anyone who is new? Being at the other end of the dais made me realise how creepy we used to be! We were felicitated by the Headmistress of the school and then were invited to start our talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;image src=&quot;/assets/images/mps2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/image&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The talk consisted of us telling our stories and sharing our regrets with the students. It was mainly ‘gyaan’ and more importantly, we had to put it in a way that they can relate to. Slowly as we progressed, surprisingly and to our amazement, those students opened up and started to ask some beguiling doubts. We were startled by their level of knowledge, enthusiasm and the curiosity to know things. They knew the basic mechanisms of a business including marketing, sales, product development and funding! Things which I personally learnt only after getting into college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever Himanshu (the other person who was speaking with me) spoke, I intently watched how the students reacted. The way they were looking up to us and expecting something great from us made me realise how influential we can be. As seniors, we have the power to mould them in the best way possible and as one of the teachers of the school put it, “Students can easily connect with people of similar ages!”. Whenever they got a chance, they used to jump out of their seat and come running to us with all sort of questions and believe me it is very difficult to convince a 16- year old school kid who won’t leave you unless he has a perfect answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;image src=&quot;/assets/images/mps3.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/image&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when we were walking out of the room after our talk, everyone in the room started clapping. In that one moment, one small moment, I lived one of the best times in my life. It feels satisfying to see that you caused a change in someone’s life. We were again felicitated in the principal’s office and were offered with snacks(a big thing for any hosteler!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even while I am writing this, I received a mail from one of the students seeking my advice. That is enough to prove that we succeeded in our endeavour in some small way. The whole experience was rejuvenating, nostalgic and enlightening to say the least. This day will certainly be remembered for a long time to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;image src=&quot;/assets/images/mps4.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/image&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Apr 2016 18:43:39 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/randomblog/what-i-learnt-by-speaking-to-school-kids</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/randomblog/what-i-learnt-by-speaking-to-school-kids</guid>
        
        
        <category>randomblog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>I Failed</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I had written in my earlier post, that I would become an early riser this year. I tried and I failed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been 2 months and 21 days and I am ashamed to share that I woke up early only for 23 days. It doesn’t mean that I hated waking up early, I loved it. The serenity, the calmness and the solitude was addictive, but it wasn’t addictive enough to wake an lazy ass like me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried many things. I read a lot. I made a morning routine. I applied all the technicalities of making a habit as explained by Charles Duhigg. I spent an hour identifying the cues and rewards and made a 15-day plan for the same. I followed it for some days and then I just stopped. Meditating in the morning was refreshing and so was exercising and drinking a cup of warm lemon water. Yet I couldn’t continue it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole experiment made me to doubt myself. I had always thought myself to be someone who cannot persist with one thing. And this whole incident proved it to me. It is very agonizing to know your mistakes and yet be helpless to solve it. The failure may be due to the fact that my schedule is unpredictable. Whatever may it be, one thing I know for sure – I failed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, for the time being, I quit and I no longer will be trying to wake up early. I will come back to it, once I finish with my engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS. I have my whole experiment documented. If anyone wants to try it, I will be more than happy to share!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2016 18:43:39 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/randomblog/i-failed</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/randomblog/i-failed</guid>
        
        
        <category>randomblog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Kasol : A place closest to Heaven</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I woke up to the roller-coaster ride of our Himachal State Transport bus when it reached Bhunter(a small town before Manali). Last night was tough after being stalled at Ambala Cant for more than 4 hours waiting for our bus to which we finally gave up and boarded the local state transport bus. But as soon as we got down at Bhunter, the cold air brought a sense of freshness in our bodies. We had to search out our bags for warm clothes because it was damn cold. We looked somewhat like this –&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;image src=&quot;/assets/images/kasol1.jpg&quot;&gt; &lt;/image&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kasol was still an hour ride from Bhunter. You ditch the Manali road and follow the Parvati for an hour, on a life-threatening road full of turns and zig-zags. Reaching Kasol after a unvarying drive, I was in a tizzy, partly out of hunger and partly out of the happy Himalayan wind.  The moment we reached Kasol, we saw a bunch of hippies strolling down the narrow roads of Kasol evidently making most of the moment. The red-and-white mobile telephony tower stands right at the edge of the river that divides Old Kasol and New Kasol. There is a bridge in the middle of the town and a few restaurants here and there, but that is all. The main beauty of this infamous town lies within, and you had to explore to find it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;image src=&quot;/assets/images/kasol2.jpg&quot;&gt; &lt;/image&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We headed straight to the riverside to catch River Parvati wildly flapping its way across this tiny Himalayan village. The Sun was just coming out. A dog was crossing the river on an old, rickety bridge(which also led straight to the party town – Chalal). There was wind in my hair and I was content in that one moment of awe. We sat there, looking at each other and then gazing upon the backdrop of the Himalayas. Trust me, 5 childhood friends meeting after a long time could feel the intensity of this moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;image src=&quot;/assets/images/kasol3.jpg&quot;&gt; &lt;/image&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The subtle moment was disturbed by our crave for rest. Some hours of sleep was enough to get us back in action mode. As such there are not many things to do in Kasol. You could either trek to Malana, Tosh or KheerGanga. But for the first evening, we chose to sit ideally near the riverbanks and just breathe. There are many good places to eat, like a good breakfast at German Bakery or a finger licking meal at Little Italy. At night, we headed out to Chalal to experience the much talked about party in the valley. Because it was the last few hours of the party, we somehow sneaked in and danced to a few last songs. The trail back to our rooms was in total darkness, walking side by side river Parvati to guide us. It seemed quite ironic to be guided by the gregarious river when we are the ones to pollute it in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;image src=&quot;/assets/images/kasol4.jpg&quot;&gt; &lt;/image&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day, we trekked to Manikaran which turned out to be a sacred place for the Sikhs. A word of caution, there are very few ATMs in this area and unfortunately not all work every time. So carry enough cash always. Then we took a detour and climbed a mountain which seemed accessible from the banks of the gurudwara. But as we kept on climbing, the peak seemed to be mocking us by getting higher and higher. In the end, as it always turns out Nature won. But the view was enthralling and worth every drop of sweat spent for climbing up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;image src=&quot;/assets/images/kasol5.jpg&quot;&gt; &lt;/image&gt;
&lt;image src=&quot;/assets/images/kasol6.jpg&quot;&gt; &lt;/image&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone has a different kind of tale to tell when they visit Kasol. We had a tale of nostalgia, we had some stories of the past to remember and a promise of making many more. Kasol helps you to slow down a bit in this fast paced world, slow down and be grateful for every tiny little thing. It is not just a place on the map, it is that tranquillity that comes with your eyes sparkling every time you see the starlit night sky or with the way you open up with your best friends and relive the younger carefree days. It forces you to do certain things which will stay as a lasting memory of the trip. There was indeed something different in that place which makes us crave to experience it once again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;image src=&quot;/assets/images/kasol7.jpg&quot;&gt; &lt;/image&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2016 18:43:39 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/travel/kasol-place-closest-to-heaven</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/travel/kasol-place-closest-to-heaven</guid>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
